<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

 <title>iobio</title>
 <link href="http://localhost:4000/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
 <link href="http://localhost:4000/"/>
 <updated>2018-02-28T14:44:22-07:00</updated>
 <id>http://localhost:4000</id>
 <author>
   <name>Chase Miller</name>
   <email>chmille4@gmail.com</email>
 </author>

 
 <entry>
   <title>ClinVar variants, gnomAD, affected status</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2017/09/29/gene_2.5.0/"/>
   <updated>2017-09-29T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2017/09/29/gene_2.5.0</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Release 2.5.0 introduces some important improvements to the gene.iobio app.  Key among these is the new ‘ClinVar Variants’ panel that shows all known ClinVar variants for a gene.  There are also a number of exciting features in this release including gnomAD allele frequencies and advanced variant filtering based on parent and sibling affected status.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;clinvar-variants&quot;&gt;ClinVar Variants&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A new panel has been introduced to gene.iobio to show clinically relevant variants known in a gene.  The app accesses the weekly refreshed ClinVar variants file to show either summary level variant counts per exon or detail level variants across the gene. Click on one of the radio buttons to display the relevant chart.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;text-align:center&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;/public/images/blog/gene_2.5.0/known_variants_card.png&quot; class=&quot;shadow-z-2&quot; style=&quot;width:80%;margin:10px 0px 25px 0px;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are three ways to view summary variant counts across the gene. The ‘exon chart’ shows ClinVar variant counts categorized as pathogenic, benign, other, and unknown, summarized per exon.  Here we show the ClinVar counts for gene PDHA1, which have the most ClinVar variants in exon 11 and 12.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/public/images/blog/gene_2.5.0/pdha1_clinvar_exon_chart.png&quot; class=&quot;shadow-z-2&quot; style=&quot;width:100%;margin:10px 0px 25px 0px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can also switch to a bar chart or or area chart views to see the distribution of variant across the entire gene.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/public/images/blog/gene_2.5.0/pdha1_clinvar_bar_chart.png&quot; class=&quot;shadow-z-2&quot; style=&quot;width:100%;margin:10px 0px  25px 0px;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/public/images/blog/gene_2.5.0/pdha1_clinvar_area_chart.png&quot; class=&quot;shadow-z-2&quot; style=&quot;width:100%;margin:0px 0px 25px 0px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Click on the ‘Variants’ radio button to view all pathogenic and likely pathogenic variants for the selected gene.  Hover over or click on variants to see the phenotype/disorder associated with this variant.  This can be useful when a variant of unknown significance appears for the proband and you would like to ascertain if other variants in the same region have been associated with the proband’s phenotype(s).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/public/images/blog/gene_2.5.0/pdha1_clinvar_variants.png&quot; class=&quot;shadow-z-2&quot; style=&quot;width:100%;margin:0px 0px 25px 0px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To view non-pathogenic variants, click on the dropdown to select other categories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;text-align:center&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;/public/images/blog/gene_2.5.0/known_variants_filter_dropdown.png&quot; class=&quot;shadow-z-2&quot; style=&quot;width:270px;margin:0px 0px 25px 0px;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By default, the app filters by pathogenic and likely pathogenic ClinVar variants because, as the figure below illustrates, a few genes have thousands variants in ClinVar.  Most genes have under 200 ClinVar variants, which is well within the range of displaying in gene.iobio.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/public/images/blog/gene_2.5.0/clinvar_counts_all.png&quot; class=&quot;shadow-z-2&quot; style=&quot;width:100%;margin:0px 0px 25px 0px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/public/images/blog/gene_2.5.0/clinvar_counts_top_50_genes.png&quot; class=&quot;shadow-z-2&quot; style=&quot;width:100%;margin:0px 0px 25px 0px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;gnomad-allele-frequencies&quot;&gt;gnomAD Allele Frequencies&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the upgrade to VEP version 90, gene.iobio is now able to display allele frequencies from &lt;a href=&quot;https://macarthurlab.org/2017/02/27/the-genome-aggregation-database-gnomad/&quot;&gt;gnomAD&lt;/a&gt;.  These allele frequencies come from exome sequence data from 123,136 individuals and whole genome sequencing from 15,496 individuals.  As the figure illustrates below, this represents a much larger sample set.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;text-align:center&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;/public/images/blog/gene_2.5.0/exacv2_barplot_cut.png&quot; class=&quot;shadow-z-2&quot; style=&quot;width:400px;margin:10px 0px 25px 0px;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The overall gnomAD allele frequency as well as those for each population appear in the tooltip in gene.iobio.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;text-align:center&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;/public/images/blog/gene_2.5.0/tooltip_gnomad_af.png&quot; class=&quot;shadow-z-2&quot; style=&quot;width:80%;margin:10px 0px 25px 0px;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;advancing-filtering-on-affected-status&quot;&gt;Advancing filtering on Affected Status&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have added the ability to filter variants according presence in affected samples and absence in unaffected samples.  A coming release will expand filtering for autosomal dominant, x-linked, and compound heterozygous inheritance patterns, but with sometimes ambiguous phenotype designations or varied penetrance, a more nuanced filtering is sometimes required.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the ‘Filter panel’, under ‘Advanced filtering’, checkboxes for affected and unaffected samples will allow fine-grained filtering.  For example, checking an unaffected sibling would exclude any variants that exist in an unaffected sibling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;text-align:center&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;/public/images/blog/gene_2.5.0/filtering_affected_status.png&quot; class=&quot;shadow-z-2&quot; style=&quot;width:40%;margin:0px 0px 25px 0px;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;whats-next&quot;&gt;What’s next&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stay tuned! Our next release of gene.iobio will allow a pre-compute step to generate a list of variants across the genome that have a rare allele frequency and a high or moderate impact, allowing genome-wide variant analysis in cases where a well-defined gene list is either not available or does not reveal any candidate variants.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Loading data into gene.iobio</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2017/09/27/loading-data/"/>
   <updated>2017-09-27T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2017/09/27/loading-data</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Gene.iobio accesses variant and sequence alignment files to perform real-time analysis.  This blog post explains how to load your data files.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;file-formats&quot;&gt;File formats&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;vcf-file&quot;&gt;VCF file&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main input to gene.iobio is the variant file.  You will need access to a VCF file that has been compressed and indexed.  If you have a VCF file, but it has not been compressed and indexed, you can learn more in the blog post &lt;a href=&quot;/2015/09/03/install-run-tabix/&quot;&gt;Compressing and indexing VCF files&lt;/a&gt;.  The app will need access to both the compressed VCF and the index file.  For example, the demo variant data shown in gene.iobio uses these files:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;
platinum-exome.vcf.gz
platinum-exome.vcf.gz.tbi
&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;bam-file-optional&quot;&gt;BAM file (optional)&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The other input to gene.iobio is the sequence alignment file, using the BAM format.  When provided, the sequence alignment files are used in the app to analyze coverage and call variants on-demand for genes of interest.  These are very large files and normally are stored in this binary form.  The app will need access to both the BAM file and its index file.  For example, the demo sequence alignment data for the proband uses these files:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;
NA12878.exome.bam
NA12878.exome.bam.bai
&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Occasionally, you might have access to the BAM files, but not the VCF files because the pipeline has yet to complete the variant calling step.  No problem.  You can load the BAM file(s) without the VCF files and the app will automatically call variants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;bookmarked-variants-file-optional&quot;&gt;Bookmarked Variants file (optional)&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Output from gene.iobio is stored in a comma separated or tab separated file.  This file contains any variants that have been
bookmarked in the app and represent the variants of interest that are being evaluated.  Please see the &lt;a href=&quot;/2017/04/26/gene_2.3.0/&quot;&gt;gene 2.3.0 blog post&lt;/a&gt; to learn more about bookmarking variants.  There is also a &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/JlXoBlWvniE&quot; target=&quot;_new&quot;&gt;Saving your Analysis video&lt;/a&gt; that walks you through this functionality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;where-is-your-data-stored&quot;&gt;Where is your data stored?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can load data files into gene.iobio by either accessing the files from your local drive or from a URL if the files are accessible from a web server. For example, the demo data is stored on an Amazon S3 bucket, so the URL for the variant file looks like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;
https://s3.amazonaws.com/iobio/samples/vcf/platinum-exome.vcf.gz
&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this case, the index file is stored in the same bucket.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;
https://s3.amazonaws.com/iobio/samples/vcf/platinum-exome.vcf.gz.tbi
&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But if the index file is available from a different URL path, you can check the button ‘Separate URL for index files’ to specify the URL to the index file.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;margin-top:80px;margin-bottom:80px&quot;&gt;
	&lt;hr style=&quot;border-width:5px; margin-left:100px; margin-right:100px;&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;div style=&quot;margin-left:100px; margin-right:100px;&quot;&gt;
	&lt;h4&gt;No lengthy upload required&lt;/h4&gt;
	Gene.iobio streams data to the backend services in gene-sized chunks, so there you can start analyzing your data as soon
	as the files have been specified.
	&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;hr style=&quot;border-width:5px; margin-left:100px; margin-right:100px;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-files-dialog&quot;&gt;The Files dialog&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To specify your data files, click on the ‘Files’ link in the nav bar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/public/images/blog/loading_data/nav_bar.png&quot; style=&quot;width:80%;margin:0px 0px 25px 0px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Specify your data files from the Files dialog.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/public/images/blog/loading_data/files_dialog.png&quot; style=&quot;width:100%; margin:0px 0px 15px 0px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If your files are stored locally, selected ‘Choose VCF file’ from the ‘Variants’ dropdown.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/public/images/blog/loading_data/choose_files.png&quot; style=&quot;width:180px;margin:0px auto 15px 180px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;multi-select both&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; the vcf.gz and the vcf.gz.tbi files.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/public/images/blog/loading_data/file_chooser.png&quot; style=&quot;width:500px;margin:0px 0px 15px 0px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For Trio analysis, specify the files for Mother and Father.  Additionally, you can specify affected and unaffected sibs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/public/images/blog/loading_data/trio.png&quot; style=&quot;width:100%; margin:0px 0px 15px 0px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you would like to load previously bookmarked variants, click on the ‘Bookmark files’ button and then specify the file format.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/public/images/blog/loading_data/bookmark_files.png&quot; style=&quot;width:80%; margin:0px 0px 15px 0px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the file is selected, the bookmarks will load and show in the left hand panel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/public/images/blog/loading_data/bookmarks_loaded.png&quot; class=&quot;shadow-z-2&quot; style=&quot;width:300px; margin:0px 0px 15px 120px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Coverage analysis</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2017/07/11/coverage/"/>
   <updated>2017-07-11T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2017/07/11/coverage</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A new version of &lt;a href=&quot;http://gene.iobio.io/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;gene.iobio&lt;/a&gt; is up, and this one has a really big feature addition that is really powerful. This update will help identify possible false negative calls due to data insufficiency, and is extremely important in any diagnostic analysis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;updates-to-the-user-interface&quot;&gt;Updates to the user interface&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The best way to see the power of this update is through an example, so we will use the &lt;a href=&quot;http://gene.iobio.io/?species=Human&amp;amp;rel0=proband&amp;amp;rel1=mother&amp;amp;rel2=father&amp;amp;build=GRCh37&amp;amp;rel=mother&amp;amp;name0=NA12878&amp;amp;vcf0=https://s3.amazonaws.com/iobio/samples/vcf/platinum-exome.vcf.gz&amp;amp;tbi0=&amp;amp;bam0=https://s3.amazonaws.com/iobio/samples/bam/NA12878.exome.bam&amp;amp;bai0=&amp;amp;sample0=NA12878&amp;amp;name1=NA12891&amp;amp;vcf1=https://s3.amazonaws.com/iobio/samples/vcf/platinum-exome.vcf.gz&amp;amp;tbi1=&amp;amp;bam1=https://s3.amazonaws.com/iobio/samples/bam/NA12891.exome.bam&amp;amp;bai1=&amp;amp;sample1=NA12891&amp;amp;name2=NA12892&amp;amp;vcf2=https://s3.amazonaws.com/iobio/samples/vcf/platinum-exome.vcf.gz&amp;amp;tbi2=&amp;amp;bam2=https://s3.amazonaws.com/iobio/samples/bam/NA12892.exome.bam&amp;amp;bai2=&amp;amp;sample2=NA12892&amp;amp;gene=AIRE&amp;amp;genes=RAI1,AIRE,MYLK2,PDGFB,PDHA1&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;demo dataset&lt;/a&gt; so that you can follow along. Imagine that we have a patient suffering from autoimmune polyendocrinopathy-candidiasis-ectodermal dystrophy (APECED). We know that mutations in the AIRE gene can be associated with this disorder, so we are using gene.iobio to check for any mutations. The dataset we are looking at is modified public data, not a real patient, but in this example, we see no variants in the AIRE gene that stand out as interesting (e.g. no annotations suggesting likely pathogenicity). We might be tempted to move on and look at other genes, but before we do, let’s take a closer look at the coverage for the proband.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/public/images/blog/coverage/AIRE.png&quot; style=&quot;width:90%; margin:15px 0px 15px 0px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The coverage track shows how the coverage varies across the gene for each sample. We can see that this is exome sequencing as we only see coverage across the exons, and nothing in the intronic regions. One thing stands out for the proband though. Exon 3 appears coloured in red in the gene model, and has a warning symbol to alert you to the fact that the coverage in this exon fails the default parameters for defining a “passing” exon. Hovering over the exon shows the coverage metrics (mean, median, min, max, etc.) for the exon, as well as which metrics “fail”. In this case, the exon has been completely skipped, so there is zero coverage across the whole exon. This means that no variant caller would be able to identify mutations in this exon, as there is no data - but they would not alert the user to the potential problem. We can see that both parents are hets for a likely pathogenic variant in this exon, so it is possible the child has inherited two bad copies of this gene; but we would never know! In this case, it would be important to resequence this gene in the proband and look for this variant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr style=&quot;border-width:5px; margin-left:100px; margin-right:100px;&quot; /&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;margin-left:100px; margin-right:100px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Filtering metrics&lt;/h4&gt;
There are a number of different metrics that are tested to determine if an exon &quot;fails&quot;. The user can set the cutoffs for these metrics in the filter panel (5). The values that can be set are:
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-left:100px; margin-right:100px;&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;mean&lt;/strong&gt;: By default, the mean coverage in an exon must be greater than 30 to pass.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-left:100px; margin-right:100px;&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;median&lt;/strong&gt;: By default, the median coverage in an exon must be greater than 30 to pass.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-left:100px; margin-right:100px;&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;min&lt;/strong&gt;: By default, the minimum observed coverage in an exon must be greater than 10. It is certainly possible that an exon has adequate median coverage, but one, or a handful, of nucleotides have very low coverage.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;hr style=&quot;border-width:5px; margin-left:100px; margin-right:100px;&quot; /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;filtering-genes-on-coverage&quot;&gt;Filtering genes on coverage&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is really important to visualize the coverage problems when looking at a gene, but we need to be sure that you look at all genes that harbour coverage problems. Gene.iobio helps you do this. Again using the &lt;a href=&quot;http://gene.iobio.io/?species=Human&amp;amp;rel0=proband&amp;amp;rel1=mother&amp;amp;rel2=father&amp;amp;build=GRCh37&amp;amp;rel=mother&amp;amp;name0=NA12878&amp;amp;vcf0=https://s3.amazonaws.com/iobio/samples/vcf/platinum-exome.vcf.gz&amp;amp;tbi0=&amp;amp;bam0=https://s3.amazonaws.com/iobio/samples/bam/NA12878.exome.bam&amp;amp;bai0=&amp;amp;sample0=NA12878&amp;amp;name1=NA12891&amp;amp;vcf1=https://s3.amazonaws.com/iobio/samples/vcf/platinum-exome.vcf.gz&amp;amp;tbi1=&amp;amp;bam1=https://s3.amazonaws.com/iobio/samples/bam/NA12891.exome.bam&amp;amp;bai1=&amp;amp;sample1=NA12891&amp;amp;name2=NA12892&amp;amp;vcf2=https://s3.amazonaws.com/iobio/samples/vcf/platinum-exome.vcf.gz&amp;amp;tbi2=&amp;amp;bam2=https://s3.amazonaws.com/iobio/samples/bam/NA12892.exome.bam&amp;amp;bai2=&amp;amp;sample2=NA12892&amp;amp;gene=RAI1&amp;amp;genes=RAI1,AIRE,MYLK2,PDGFB,PDHA1&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;demo dataset&lt;/a&gt;, we will demonstrate how. Once we open the demo data, we select “Analyze all genes”. In a few seconds, all the gene badges at the top of the page show a summary of each gene.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/public/images/blog/coverage/gene_badges.png&quot; style=&quot;width:80%; margin:8px 0px 10px 0px;&quot; align=&quot;middle&quot; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both AIRE and PDHA1 badges include a glyph indicating coverage problems (&lt;img src=&quot;/public/images/blog/coverage/coverage_glyph.png&quot; style=&quot;width:2%; margin:0px 0px;&quot; /&gt;), so we know we need to take a look at them. If the gene list is large, rather than looking through all these gene badges, we can apply a filter to identify genes harbouring coverage problems. To do this, we select the “Filter” option (1 in the above figure), and from the side panel, click the “Insufficient coverage in exons” button (2).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/public/images/blog/coverage/filter.png&quot; style=&quot;width:90%; margin:15px 0px 15px 0px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The summary (3) shows us that two genes fail this filter, and the gene badges are now sorted to put these genes first (4). In this case, the PDHA1 and AIRE genes are shown first, with the other genes fading into the background. Now we can look at each of these genes in turn to identify what the problems are, and if we think they are a genuine problem that we need to take action on.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Gene.iobio 2.3.0</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2017/04/26/gene_2.3.0/"/>
   <updated>2017-04-26T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2017/04/26/gene_2.3.0</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A new version of &lt;a href=&quot;http://gene.iobio.io/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;gene.iobio&lt;/a&gt; is now up and running, featuring several improvements that are another big step forwards!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;outputting-variants&quot;&gt;Outputting variants&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &quot;bookmarks&quot; functionality lets us store variants that we are interested in, so that we can easily jump back to them whenever we want. We heard from many users that they want to be able to output these variants, either to a VCF file, or to an Excel spreadsheet. We now support this functionality. If you select a variant (either by clicking on a variant, or a column in the &quot;Ranked variants&quot; table), a tooltip appears showing a whole host of information about the variant. In the bottom left corner of this tooltip, we can click to &quot;bookmark this variant&quot;. This variant is now stored. By clicking on the &quot;Bookmarks&quot; tab at the top of the page, we can look at a summary of all bookmarks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/public/images/blog/gene_2.3.0/bookmarks.png&quot; style=&quot;width:100%; margin:0px 0px 0px 0px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using the &quot;Export&quot; option, we can choose to export the bookmarked variants as either an Excel, or a VCF file.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/public/images/blog/gene_2.3.0/export.png&quot; style=&quot;width:65%; margin:20px 0px 0px 160px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whichever option you choose, the output file contains a list of all the variants, along with all of the annotation information that was available within gene.iobio.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;calling-variants&quot;&gt;Calling variants&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have removed the &quot;Call variants&quot; tab from the top of gene.iobio and instead, integrated calling into the &quot;Selected genes&quot; panel at the top of the screen. There have also been a number of improvements to the user interface, that we think really improve the user experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/public/images/blog/gene_2.3.0/calling.png&quot; style=&quot;width:100%; margin:20px 0px 0px 0px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;1-which-genes-to-call-variants-for&quot;&gt;1. Which genes to call variants for?&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the &quot;Call variants&quot; dropdown you can choose to call variants in the gene that you are currently looking at, or you can choose to call variants in all the genes in your list. Once selected, gene will start calling variants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;2-calling-progress&quot;&gt;2. Calling progress&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The coloured bars keep track of how many genes have been analyzed, and how many have had new variants called using Freebayes within gene.iobio. In the demo data example above, there are five genes in the list. The top (blue) bar shows how many genes have had the &quot;loaded&quot; variants, i.e. those in the selected VCF file, analyzed, and the lower (green) bar shows how many genes have had variants called. These bars are explained in more detail in the Filtering variants section below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The gene badges also contain checkmarks to make it clear what analyses have occurred. In the above example, the loaded variants have been analyzed, but no variant calling has happened for the AIRE and PDGFB genes. Both these genes have the check mark (&lt;img src=&quot;/public/images/blog/gene_2.3.0/single.png&quot; style=&quot;width:2%; margin:-2px 0px;&quot; /&gt;) that indicates this. RAI1 and PDHA1 have two check marks (&lt;img src=&quot;/public/images/blog/gene_2.3.0/both.png&quot; style=&quot;width:3%; margin:-2px 0px;&quot; /&gt;). The blue check mark indicates that the loaded variants have been analyzed and the green one, that variants have been called. Finally, MYLK2 shows &lt;img src=&quot;/public/images/blog/gene_2.3.0/both_called.png&quot; style=&quot;width:3%; margin:-2px 0px;&quot; /&gt;. Again, the loaded variants have been analyzed, but the called check mark is now in a green circle. This check mark is used to identify when uniquely called variants are present in the gene. The simple green check mark, by contrast, means that variant calling has taken place, but no unique variants were discovered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;3-filtering-variants&quot;&gt;3. Filtering variants&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this example, I have already applied variant filters. The panel at the left shows the results from applying the standard set of filters. Next to the &quot;Known pathogenic&quot; filter, we are presented with three glyphs. The first, &lt;img src=&quot;/public/images/blog/gene_2.3.0/missing.png&quot; style=&quot;width:3%; margin:0px 0px;&quot; /&gt;, is provided as a warning to note that not all of the genes have been analyzed. Next we see &lt;img src=&quot;/public/images/blog/gene_2.3.0/loaded_count.png&quot; style=&quot;width:3%; margin:0px 0px;&quot; /&gt;. This is a count of the number of genes with a &lt;i&gt;loaded&lt;/i&gt; variant that passes the filters. Finally, we can see the number of genes with a &lt;i&gt;called&lt;/i&gt; variant that passes the filters (&lt;img src=&quot;/public/images/blog/gene_2.3.0/called_count.png&quot; style=&quot;width:3%; margin:0px 0px;&quot; /&gt;). So in this case, there is one gene with a &lt;i&gt;loaded&lt;/i&gt; variant, and one gene with a &lt;i&gt;called&lt;/i&gt; variant that counts as a &quot;Known pathogenic&quot; variant. But how do we know which genes these counts are referring to?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/public/images/blog/gene_2.3.0/badges.png&quot; style=&quot;width:75%; margin:20px 0px 30px 100px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The gene badges are automatically sorted so that the genes with variants that pass filters appear to the left. So we can see that the furthest left gene badge is for RAI1, followed by MYLK2. Both these genes have other glyphs that indicate properties of the contained variants (see this &lt;a href=&quot;http://iobio.io/2016/03/28/multi-gene/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;post&lt;/a&gt; for more details), whereas the remaining genes do not. So we know that these are the only two genes we need to look in. Only MYLK2 has the &lt;img src=&quot;/public/images/blog/gene_2.3.0/both_called.png&quot; style=&quot;width:3%; margin:0px 0px;&quot; /&gt;, indicating that variants were called in this gene, so we know that MYLK2 contains the &lt;i&gt;called&lt;/i&gt; known pathogenic variant, and RAI1 contains the &lt;i&gt;loaded&lt;/i&gt; known pathogenic variant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, gene provides a visual summary of the analyses that have occured and the filtering results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/public/images/blog/gene_2.3.0/bars.png&quot; style=&quot;width:50%; margin:20px 0px 30px 200px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The top bar refers to the &lt;i&gt;loaded&lt;/i&gt; variant (remember, these are the variants pulled from the selected vcf file). The bar is split into two. The first segment (in blue) refers to the number of genes that contain a variant passing currently selected filters. In this case, that is one gene. Then we see the remainder of the bar is gray, indicating that the other four genes have been analyzed, but do not contain any variants that pass the filters. The bottom bar works in the same way, but for the &lt;i&gt;called&lt;/i&gt; variants. We again see that one gene contains a variant passing the filters. We then see that two genes have had variants called, but no passing variants are present in them (the gray segment). Finally, we see a white segment, indicating that two genes have not yet had variants called. We can confirm this by noting that the AIRE and PDGFB gene badges do not contain the green checkmarks indicating calling has happened.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We hope that these improvements will make it even easier to understand your data and, as always, we encourage you to give &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:iobioproject@gmail.com&quot; subject=&quot;gene.iobio suggestions&quot;&gt;feedback&lt;/a&gt; on everything &lt;strong&gt;&lt;i&gt;iobio&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; related!&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Gene.iobio 2.2.0</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2017/02/27/gene_2.2.0/"/>
   <updated>2017-02-27T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2017/02/27/gene_2.2.0</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;We are really happy to announce the latest release of &lt;a href=&quot;http://gene.iobio.io/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;gene.iobio&lt;/a&gt;; version 2.2.0. We have made a major upgrade to the user interface, as well as implementing some new features that really boost the power of analysis with gene.iobio. In this post, I am going to highlight the major changes and recommend that you take a look at the linked tutorials, which demonstrate the power of these new features. The improved filtering functionality significantly enhances gene.iobio, so I strongly urge you read that section! We have also put out a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=QiJ7wuN8LYQ&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;webcast&lt;/a&gt; to highlight some of these changes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;new-user-interface&quot;&gt;New user interface&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have made a number of changes to the basic layout of gene.iobio which we think make it more usable, but also just looks prettier! Here are a couple of the major changes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/public/images/blog/gene_2.2.0/layout.png&quot; style=&quot;width:100%; margin:20px 0px 20px 0px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;1-analysis-options&quot;&gt;1. Analysis options&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have moved the list of analysis options from the left hand side to the top of the screen. This makes the multitude of analysis options available in gene.iobio more prominent and accessible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;2-analysis-summary&quot;&gt;2. Analysis summary&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In our own analyses using gene.iobio, we sometimes lost track of how many genes we we were looking and whether or not they were all analyzed. To solve this, we have added a summary of analyzed genes. This provides an up-to-date count of genes we have in our list, and how many of them have been analyzed. If we use the &quot;Analyze all genes&quot; function, gene.iobio will march through all the genes in the list, and update this summary as analysis completes on each gene. In addition, when analysis is underway, we can see which gene is currently being analyzed. This is especially helpful when there are multiple pages of genes, and the gene currently being analyzed is on the next page.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;3-gene-list-management&quot;&gt;3. Gene list management&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can still import gene lists, or select the ACMG secondary findings genes from the &quot;Select genes&quot; tab at the top of the page, but we now have quick access to modify the gene list on the main page.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;4-legend&quot;&gt;4. Legend&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We show a lot of information about each variant using lots of different glyphs. If it isn't clear what these glyphs mean, you can now select &quot;Show legend&quot; above the &quot;Ranked variants&quot; table, and a legend describing all these glyphs is shown.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;improved-filtering&quot;&gt;Improved filtering&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The modifications to filtering have transformed gene.iobio, making it even easier and more effective in identifying variants of interest. I will use the demo dataset available in gene.iobio to show how powerful the filtering functionality, as well as how easy it is to use. To follow along, open &lt;a href=&quot;http://nv-dev.iobio.io/gene.iobio.next/?species=Human&amp;amp;rel0=proband&amp;amp;rel1=mother&amp;amp;rel2=father&amp;amp;build=GRCh37&amp;amp;rel=mother&amp;amp;name0=NA12878&amp;amp;vcf0=https://s3.amazonaws.com/iobio/samples/vcf/platinum-exome.vcf.gz&amp;amp;bam0=https://s3.amazonaws.com/iobio/samples/bam/NA12878.exome.bam&amp;amp;sample0=NA12878&amp;amp;name1=NA12891&amp;amp;vcf1=https://s3.amazonaws.com/iobio/samples/vcf/platinum-exome.vcf.gz&amp;amp;bam1=https://s3.amazonaws.com/iobio/samples/bam/NA12891.exome.bam&amp;amp;sample1=NA12891&amp;amp;name2=NA12892&amp;amp;vcf2=https://s3.amazonaws.com/iobio/samples/vcf/platinum-exome.vcf.gz&amp;amp;bam2=https://s3.amazonaws.com/iobio/samples/bam/NA12892.exome.bam&amp;amp;sample2=NA12892&amp;amp;gene=RAI1&amp;amp;genes=RAI1,AIRE,MYLK2,PDGFB,PDHA1&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;gene.iobio&lt;/a&gt; and click &quot;Analyze all genes&quot;. This will analyze the variants in each of the genes in turn. When complete, we are ready to start applying filters to identify interesting genes. Click the &quot;Filter Variants&quot; tab at the top of the page to access the filtering functionality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/public/images/blog/gene_2.2.0/filter.png&quot; style=&quot;width:100%; margin:20px 0px 0px 0px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We recommend following a hierarchy based method of variant discovery. By this, I mean that we want to start our analysis by identifying the variants most likely to be responsible for an observed phenotype, and then progressively open up our filters to allow in more and more variants. We can do this using the hierarchy of predefined filters shown in the image above. Starting at the top of this hierarchy, select &quot;Known causative&quot;. A few things just happened, so let's look at each of them in turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;1-filtering-parameters&quot;&gt;1. Filtering parameters&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A set of stringent pre-selected filtering parameters was set to identify rare variants that are known to be pathogenic. We can see what filters were applied in two places (see the image below). In the filter panel at the left, the applied filters are identified with a blue border, and at the top of the screen, the filters are explicitly listed. So, in order for a variant to pass the applied filters, it must be rare (defined in this case as having an allele frequency below 5% in both the 1000 Genomes and ExAC databases), and must be present in the ClinVar database, and annotated as either &quot;pathogenic&quot;, or &quot;likely pathogenic&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/public/images/blog/gene_2.2.0/kc.png&quot; style=&quot;width:100%; margin:20px 0px 0px 0px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;2-number-of-genes-containing-a-passing-variant&quot;&gt;2. Number of genes containing a &quot;passing&quot; variant&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you select a filter, e.g. &quot;Known causative&quot;, only genes that contain a variant passing these filters are relevant. To the right of the &quot;Known causative&quot; button, we are told that only one of the five analyzed genes contains a variant that passes these filters. We can also see this at the top of the screen; we are told that all five genes have been analyzed, and the only one gene passes the filters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you look at the gene.iobio screenshot under the &quot;Improved filtering&quot; title, each gene in the gene list has a badge at the top of the page, and the gene name is accompanied by a series of glyphs describing contained variants. If you look at the image just above, however, only the &lt;i&gt;RAI1&lt;/i&gt; gene has glyphs. Glyphs are only retained for passing variants, and since &lt;i&gt;RAI1&lt;/i&gt; is the only gene with a variant that passes the filters, this is the only gene that retains glyphs in the gene badge. By comparing the two images again, you can also see that with no filters applied, there are four variants in the &lt;i&gt;RAI1&lt;/i&gt; gene, but after filtering, we are left with a single variant in a single gene that is known to be causative for a disorder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;3-gene-sorting&quot;&gt;3. Gene sorting&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you impose filters, we have already seen that the gene list is updated to only show glyphs for genes that contain genes that pass these filters. In addition to the visualization, gene.iobio also reorders the gene badges so that the genes contained passing variants appear first; the genes are ordered according to the functional relevance of the contained genes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;de-novo-vus&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;De novo VUS&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If no &quot;Known causative&quot; variants are found, or they are ruled out, we can move to different sets of parameters. For example, we can move down the list to find &lt;i&gt;de novo&lt;/i&gt; variants of unknown significance (VUS) by selecting this button. As soon as this is clicked, we see the applied filters change - note that ClinVar's pathogenic and likely pathogenic values have a strikethrough. We are not showing any variants that fall into this category as we don't want to duplicate the variants already seen in the &quot;Known causative&quot; category. We see that there are two genes, &lt;i&gt;PDHA1&lt;/i&gt; and &lt;i&gt;PDGFB&lt;/i&gt;, that contain &lt;i&gt;de novo&lt;/i&gt; VUS variants, and that the list of genes is reordered so that these genes appear at the start of the list. The variant in &lt;i&gt;PDHA&lt;/i&gt; appears first since the variant in this gene has more serious Sift and Polyphen scores. Clicking on the gene, moves you to the gene so you can manually look at the contained variants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;manual-filtering&quot;&gt;Manual filtering&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you work through the preset filter categories, and have not identified a candidate causative variant, we can apply our own filters. First, the selected filter set can be removed by selecting &quot;Clear all&quot; at the top of the filter panel at the left of the screen. Then you can apply filters of your choosing and the gene list and count of passing genes will dynamically reorder&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Reference genomes</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2017/01/23/ref_genomes/"/>
   <updated>2017-01-23T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2017/01/23/ref_genomes</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The latest release of &lt;a href=&quot;http://gene.iobio.io/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;gene.iobio&lt;/a&gt; includes the ability to use the GRCh38 human reference genome for analysis. This is only a quick post, because we will soon be releasing a major update to gene.iobio, version 2.2.0, which includes significant updates to both the appearance and functionality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, when you use gene.iobio, you will see that when you define your input data, you can choose from a list of available of reference genomes from the “Genome Build” menu. Currently, only GRCh37 and GRCh38 human reference genomes are available, but if you would like to see other genomes, please contact us at this &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:iobioproject@gmail.com&quot; subject=&quot;gene.iobio suggestions&quot;&gt;address&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/public/images/blog/grch38/data_input.png&quot; style=&quot;width:60%; margin:40px 0px 40px 160px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you do not specifically pick a reference genome, gene.iobio will attempt to identify the build used from the headers of the selected files. If the build cannot be determined, however, gene.iobio will prompt to you to manually specify the genome to use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now keep your eyes peeled for the next upcoming release of gene that we are really excited about!&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Viewing ClinVar variants</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2016/11/03/clinvar/"/>
   <updated>2016-11-03T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2016/11/03/clinvar</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;As part of the analysis of a clinical dataset, we needed to answer a very simple question; is this exon important? In answering this question, we inadvertantly created a ClinVar variant viewer using gene.iobio.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-problem&quot;&gt;The problem&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we study a child's DNA to find the genetic basis of their disease, we typically start with a list of their genetic variants and ask if any of them have been previously implicated in the disease. Then we proceed down an analysis path, looking at variants in different categories; disease-associated genes; rare variants; variants predicted to impact protein function or expression etc. and; different inheritance modes. Occasionally, we find exons with really low coverage, so no variants could be identified in them. Here is an example of a sample with no coverage in two exons in an ACMG56 gene:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/public/images/blog/clinvar_viewer/no_coverage.png&quot; style=&quot;width:80%; margin:40px 0px 40px 80px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we saw this, the question we immediately asked was, “Are these exons important?” It might be the case that these exons are predicted to exist, but are not actually present in any expressed transcript. So we needed a quick way of checking if these exons were known to harbour any interesting variants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-solution&quot;&gt;The solution&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The solution we came up with was to ask if anybody had reported variants in these exons as being associated with a disease. One way to do this would be to look at what variants ClinVar has for this gene. So here are all the variants listed as pathogenic in ClinVar in the PMS2 gene:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/public/images/blog/clinvar_viewer/pathogenic.png&quot; style=&quot;width:80%; margin:40px 0px 40px 80px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have used the filters in gene.iobio to only show variants marked as &quot;Pathogenic&quot; in ClinVar. But the result is clear. The two exons with no coverage do harbour known pathogenic variants: in this case, associated with Lynch syndrome. This means that in prioritizing variants in this sample, we will inevitably have an incomplete analysis, since we know there are exons without data. We cannot rule out the possibility that this patient has pathogenic variants in these exons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;a-clinvar-viewer&quot;&gt;A ClinVar viewer&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I found that this was a really useful visualization to help me understand this data set, and, realised that this was an easy way of looking at ClinVar data. Follow this &lt;a href=&quot;http://gene.iobio.io/?rel0=proband&amp;amp;rel1=mother&amp;amp;rel2=father&amp;amp;gene=TP53&amp;amp;name0=proband&amp;amp;name1=mother&amp;amp;name2=father&amp;amp;sample1=10718X3&amp;amp;sample2=10718X2&amp;amp;genes=TP53&amp;amp;affectedSibs=&amp;amp;unaffectedSibs=&amp;amp;vcf0=https://s3.amazonaws.com/vcf.files/clinvar_20161003.vcf.gz&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt; to see ClinVar variants in the TP53 gene using gene.iobio. Using the filters (at the left of the screen), we can choose to view only &quot;Pathogenic&quot; variants, and you can choose different genes by typing them in at the top of the page.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/public/images/blog/clinvar_viewer/viewer.png&quot; style=&quot;width:100%; margin:40px 0px 40px 0px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you select any variant by clicking on it, the left panel is populated with information on the variant. The ClinVar clinical significance is listed along with any associated conditions. To get more information from ClinVar, just click the clinical significance and you will be redirected to the ClinVar page for this variant.
5&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/public/images/blog/clinvar_viewer/clinvar_entry.png&quot; style=&quot;width:90%; margin:40px 0px 0px 50px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;font-size:12px&quot;&gt;Binoculars icon made by &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.freepik.com&quot;&gt;Freepik&lt;/a&gt; from &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.flaticon.com&quot;&gt;www.flaticon.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>IOBIO Now in Galaxy</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2016/11/02/galaxy-integration/"/>
   <updated>2016-11-02T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2016/11/02/galaxy-integration</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;bam.iobio and vcf.iobio can now be launched directly from galaxy using your data already stored there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To give it a spin, you can use a galaxy public dataset. Login to &lt;a href=&quot;https://usegalaxy.org/&quot;&gt;galaxy&lt;/a&gt; and go to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://usegalaxy.org/library/list?#folders/Fabe1072935a8f2e4&quot;&gt;iobio demo data folder&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/public/images/blog/galaxy_integration/iobio_public_folder.png&quot; style=&quot;width: 100%; display:block; margin:auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then click on each of the two demo data files (bam and vcf) and click To History&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/public/images/blog/galaxy_integration/galaxy_to_history.png&quot; style=&quot;width: 100%; display:block; margin:auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now head back to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://usegalaxy.org/&quot;&gt;galaxy homepage&lt;/a&gt; and you should see your two files in the history panel. Click on  NA12878.autsome.bam and when it expands click on “display at bam.iobio”. You will be taken directly to bam.iobio and analysis will start automatically. As a bonus this link is also shareable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/public/images/blog/galaxy_integration/bam.iobio_galaxy.png&quot; style=&quot;width: 300px; display:block; margin:20px auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ExAC vcf file works the same way, however the index (.gz) has to be created first, which will take up to a few minutes the first time. However after it’s created once, all future analyses will be instant just like for bam files.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;video controls=&quot;&quot; loop=&quot;&quot; video=&quot;&quot; autoplay=&quot;&quot; style=&quot;width:100%; margin: 10px auto&quot;&gt;
&lt;source src=&quot;/public/images/blog/galaxy_integration/galaxy_vcf.iobio.mp4&quot; type=&quot;video/mp4&quot; /&gt;
Your browser does not support the video tag.
&lt;/video&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Gene.iobio version 2.1</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2016/09/22/gene2.1/"/>
   <updated>2016-09-22T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2016/09/22/gene2.1</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;It has been a little while since version 2 of &lt;a href=&quot;http://gene.iobio.io&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;gene.iobio&lt;/a&gt; was released, but we have now updated to version 2.1. A lot of work has gone into this update (specifically by Tony Di Sera), including the addition of some powerful features that we're sure you will find useful. In the coming weeks, we will describe these features in more detail, but some of the main updates are summarised here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;call-variants-directly-from-alignment-bam-files&quot;&gt;Call variants directly from alignment (BAM) files&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you only have VCF files and no BAM files, we can use gene.iobio to visualise the variants. We cannot visualize the underlying sequence coverage, or recall variants, however, since that would require the BAM files to be present. What happens if we only have BAM files, though and don't have VCF files? Not a problem! When we specify BAM files only for an individual or trio, gene.iobio will call variants using the BAM files and we can still perform our analysis. If we want to get a quick look at known genes before full bioinformatics pipelines have been completed, gene.iobio gives us the opportunity!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;reorder-genes-based-on-high-impact-variants&quot;&gt;Reorder genes based on high-impact variants&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In our own analyses, we often have lots of genes of interest and we have no desire to click through each gene in turn. The 'Analyze all' feature lets &lt;a href=&quot;http://gene.iobio.io&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;gene.iobio&lt;/a&gt; march through all the genes, with the results summarized in the gene badges at the top of the page. Once this analysis is complete, a new feature can be employed to resort (number 2 in the figure) these gene badges according to the variants contained in them. The gene containing the most likely causative variant will appear first and so on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/public/images/blog/gene2.1/screenshot.png&quot; style=&quot;width:100%; margin:20px 0px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;filtered-variants-displayed&quot;&gt;Filtered variants displayed&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All variants in the VCF file are displayed and appear in the 'Rank variants' table. Previously, if some variants were marked with 'PASS' in the VCF filter column, they were displayed, while remaining variants (often with '.' in the VCF filter column) were filtered out and not displayed. This can be confusing, so now all variants are displayed, reagrdless of the VCF filter string, but those not marked with 'PASS' appear greyed out in the 'Rank variants' table. This can be seen in the figure above (4). As a result, when you are looking at this table, any variant with a grey background is likely a low quality variant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;consistent-scaling-of-coverage-tracks&quot;&gt;Consistent scaling of coverage tracks&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The coverage tracks for all members of a trio (number 5 in the figure above) are now scaled consistently. This helps identify cases where the coverage is significantly different for one member of the family.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;reference-gene-sets&quot;&gt;Reference gene sets&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some genes are unique to the RefSeq or GenCode gene sets. This can lead to problems if we look at a RefSeq gene while we have GenCode selected (see 3 in the figure above), for example. Any problems associated with this have now been removed. Now, if we select a gene unique to RefSeq while we have the GenCode set selected, we are immediately moved to the RefSeq reference set and shown the canonical transcript.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;feedback&quot;&gt;Feedback&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is really important to us to ensure gene.iobio is as useful and usable as possible. We also recognise that the occasional bug creeps into the app that we don't always find ourselves. A 'Feedback' (number 1 in the figure) button has been added at the top of the app to make it easy for you to have your say. If you notice anything that is unclear, or doesn't work as you think that it should, please let us know. We will do everything in our power to address any comments. We can't address problems that we don't know you are having, so please let us know!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.freepik.com/free-vector/new-product-seal_763078.htm&quot; style=&quot;font-size:12px;&quot;&gt;New product logo designed by Freepik&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.freepik.com/free-vector/blue-square-mosiac-background_833486.htm&quot; style=&quot;font-size:12px;&quot;&gt;Background designed by Freepik&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>bam.iobio facelift</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2016/09/20/bam/"/>
   <updated>2016-09-20T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2016/09/20/bam</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The first app in the iobio family, &lt;a href=&quot;http://bam.iobio.io&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;bam.iobio&lt;/a&gt;, has had a facelift, and is now better than ever. As a demonstration, I am going to take a look at my own genome to highlight a couple of the changes. This demonstration will also show how well iobio apps play together, acting in concert to help answer interesting genomic questions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started out by selecting the bam file to look at (remember that when selecting a local file, you need to select both the bam and the bai index file together), in this case, my own genome. After a few seconds, enough data has been sampled to generate the image at the top of the page. There are a couple of noticable changes to the appearance. First, the chromosome wheel has been added in the top left corner, mirroring the reference sequence selection already implemented in the &lt;a href=&quot;http://vcf.iobio.io&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;vcf.iobio&lt;/a&gt;. This wheel makes chromosome selection, quick and easy, but also just looks great!!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/public/images/blog/bam-facelift/statement.png&quot; style=&quot;width:100%; margin:40px 0px 40px 0px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another big change is the way that &lt;a href=&quot;http://bam.iobio.io&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;bam.iobio&lt;/a&gt; now operates. Sequence reads are sampled from the whole genome and the index file is used to determine the fraction of reads that do not map anywhere to the reference sequence. Note that index files created with older versions of &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/samtools/samtools&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;samtools&lt;/a&gt; do not have the necessary information to provide this information. These reads are actually really important to help us understand the bam file we are looking at. In a perfect sequencing experiment, all of the reads originated in the genome being studied and they should all map back to the reference genome, leading to a mapping rate of 100%. We know that this never happens though, since the sampled genome does not look exactly like the reference genome. Reads coming from larger insertions, for example, will not map to reference and so will enter the BAM file as unmapped reads, bring down the mapping rate. Even accounting for these differences, we expect the mapping rate to be high, over 90%, so it is a little concerning that only 71.5% of the reads associated with my genome map to the human reference. Maybe I am a more evolved being, with lots of unique DNA, but I suspect that it is actually a result of how the DNA was sampled or problems in the sequencing experiment. Having identified a problem, I can now move to another iobio app, &lt;a href=&quot;http://taxononer.iobio.io&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;taxonomer.iobio&lt;/a&gt;, to take a look at what DNA is present in my BAM file.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/public/images/blog/bam-facelift/bacteria.png&quot; style=&quot;width:40%; margin:20px 250px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://taxononer.iobio.io&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Taxonomer.iobio&lt;/a&gt;, and the related &lt;a href=&quot;http://taxonomer.com&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;commercial version&lt;/a&gt; use the Taxonomer software developed in the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.yandell-lab.org/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Yandell&lt;/a&gt; lab at the University of Utah, to classify the metagenomic make up of a DNA sample. The image above shows the bacterial composition of the raw DNA reads generated from my sample, generated in a few seconds. This is really interesting and let's me see all of the different organisms that were present in the DNA that is associated with me. All of these bacteria are known to exist in the human microbiome, specifically, the kind of bacteria that are found in a human mouth and mucus. So, what is the conclusion to all of this? By using &lt;a href=&quot;http://bam.iobio.io&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;bam.iobio&lt;/a&gt; to look at the quality of my DNA sequencing, I was quickly able to spot a possible contamination problem. Following up on this with &lt;a href=&quot;http://taxononer.iobio.io&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;taxonomer.iobio&lt;/a&gt;, I was able to determine that the DNA was contaminated with DNA from bacteria often found in a human mouth. In a couple of minutes, I identified that my DNA was harvested from a spit sample, rather than from blood. Since I know that I used a spit kit, I know this is the correct conclusion! But, if the source of the DNA you're working with is unknown, these &lt;a href=&quot;http://iobio.iobio.io&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;iobio&lt;/a&gt; tools give you a very quick way of finding out.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Using bookmarks</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2016/08/03/bookmarks/"/>
   <updated>2016-08-03T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2016/08/03/bookmarks</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;general-use&quot;&gt;General use&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;http://gene.iobio.io&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;gene.iobio&lt;/a&gt; version 2 blog series marches on with a discussion of bookmarks. A future post in this series will talk about importing bookmarks from external tools, e.g. &lt;a href=&quot;https://gemini.readthedocs.org/en/latest/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Gemini&lt;/a&gt;. In this post, I will demonstrate how to use bookmarks, beginning with the &lt;a href=&quot;http://gene.iobio.io/?rel0=proband&amp;amp;rel1=mother&amp;amp;rel2=father&amp;amp;name0=&amp;amp;vcf0=https://s3.amazonaws.com/iobio/gene/wgs_platinum/platinum-trio.vcf.gz&amp;amp;bam0=https://s3.amazonaws.com/iobio/gene/wgs_platinum/NA12878.bam&amp;amp;name1=&amp;amp;vcf1=https://s3.amazonaws.com/iobio/gene/wgs_platinum/platinum-trio.vcf.gz&amp;amp;bam1=https://s3.amazonaws.com/iobio/gene/wgs_platinum/NA12892.bam&amp;amp;name2=&amp;amp;vcf2=https://s3.amazonaws.com/iobio/gene/wgs_platinum/platinum-trio.vcf.gz&amp;amp;bam2=https://s3.amazonaws.com/iobio/gene/wgs_platinum/NA12891.bam&amp;amp;sample0=NA12878&amp;amp;sample1=NA12891&amp;amp;sample2=NA12892&amp;amp;genes=RAI1&amp;amp;gene=RAI1&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;RAI1&lt;/a&gt; usecase. In this gene, we can see a variant that is associated with smith-magenis syndrome and is marked as pathogenic in ClinVar (this is the variant at the far left in the ranking table and marked with the &lt;img src=&quot;/public/images/blog/multiple-genes/clinvar.png&quot; style=&quot;width:2%; margin:0px 0px;&quot; /&gt; symbol). If we click on the variant (either clicking the column in the ranking table, or clicking on the actual variant in the proband variants), details about the variant will appear in a mouseover and in the panel to the left of the screen as shown below:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/public/images/blog/bookmarks/bookmark-select.png&quot; style=&quot;width:75%; margin:20px 100px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can &quot;bookmark&quot; this variant by clicking &quot;Bookmark&quot; in either the left panel, or in the tooltip. Once bookmarked, we are free to continue looking at other variants, or analyzing other genes, knowing that we can easily return to this variant if needed. To return to the variant, we will use the &quot;Bookmarks&quot; panel to the left of the screen. If we open the bookmarks panel, we see the following at the left of the screen:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/public/images/blog/bookmarks/bookmark-panel.png&quot; style=&quot;width:60%; margin:20px 150px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The glyphs associated with the variant are visible along with the gene, coordinate and alleles, so we can quickly identify the important attributes of the variant (see &lt;a href=&quot;http://iobio.io/2016/03/28/multi-gene/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; for an explanation of the glyphs) - in this case a &quot;high impact&quot;, ClinVar pathogenic, recessive variant. Clicking on the variant will return us to the correct gene and highlight the variant. All bookmarked variants will have the &lt;img src=&quot;/public/images/blog/bookmarks/bookmark-glyph.png&quot; style=&quot;width:2%; margin:0px 0px;&quot; /&gt; glyph in the ranked variants table, and the glyph will appear in the gene badge at the top of the page - if multiple genes are open - (&lt;img src=&quot;/public/images/blog/bookmarks/gene-badge.png&quot; /&gt;), so you will always know which genes contain bookmarked variants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;editing-and-exporting-bookmarks&quot;&gt;Editing and exporting bookmarks&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the &quot;Bookmarks&quot; panel at the left, bookmarks can be:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Selected; this will load the gene containing that variant and highlight the bookmarked variant,&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Starred, allowing important variants to be identified among all the bookmarked variants,&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Removed by clicking edit and then the red cross that appears next to the bookmark. &lt;img src=&quot;/public/images/blog/bookmarks/bookmark-delete.png&quot; style=&quot;width:45%; margin:20px 200px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Imported, which will be discussed in a later blog post,&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Exported. When we've finished analysis with gene.iobio, click on the &quot;Export&quot; button and we are given the option of exporting all variants, or just those that are starred. Choosing one of these options then opens a new tab, containing a text output of all the variants. This output includes not only positional information, but the ref and alt alleles, inheritance mode and gene. This file can then be saved, and can be imported back into gene.iobio at a later date.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>iobio is hiring</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2016/06/29/web-dev-hire/"/>
   <updated>2016-06-29T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2016/06/29/web-dev-hire</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The iobio project is seeking a highly motivated web developer / bioinformatician to work with the &lt;a href=&quot;http://marthlab.org/&quot;&gt;Marth lab&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://frameshift.io&quot;&gt;Frameshift Genomics&lt;/a&gt;. See all the information &lt;a href=&quot;http://frameshift.io/public/images/web_developer_1.pdf&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and email us at &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:frameshiftlabs@gmail.com&quot;&gt;frameshiftlabs@gmail.com&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Why Am I Sick? With This Tool, Doctors Could Know At a Glance</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2016/06/15/radio-interview/"/>
   <updated>2016-06-15T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2016/06/15/radio-interview</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Here's a &lt;a href=&quot;http://healthcare.utah.edu/the-scope/shows.php?shows=0_0zg5yupn&quot;&gt;radio interview&lt;/a&gt; I did about taxonomer.iobio.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Gene.iobio museum exhibit</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2016/05/31/museum-exhibit-gene/"/>
   <updated>2016-05-31T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2016/05/31/museum-exhibit-gene</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Gene.iobio is currently featured at the Natural History Museum of Utah's exhibit &lt;a href=&quot;https://nhmu.utah.edu/genome&quot;&gt;Genome:  Unlocking Life's Code&lt;/a&gt;.   NHGRI partnered with the Smithsonian's National Museum of Natural History (NMNH) to create an &lt;a href=&quot;https://unlockinglifescode.org/about&quot;&gt;exhibit&lt;/a&gt; that chronicles the advancements in genomics and showcases how these discoveries impact people's lives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now the exhibit is traveling around the country with it's current stop at the University of Utah from May 21st through September 5th.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When Gabor Marth was invited to show our lab's work at the exhibit, we jumped at the chance.  IOBIO is the perfect platform to engage museum visitors since it involves real-time analysis and provides intuitive visualizations.  With the growing popularity of personal genomics along with the promising advancements in precision medicine, we chose to feature the gene.iobio app.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;http://learngene.iobio.io/exhibit.html&quot;&gt;gene.iobio exhibit&lt;/a&gt; has two components.  A two minute video introduces the visitor to key concepts and gives an overview of gene.iobio's functionality.  Clicking on 'Start here' plays the introductory video.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;text-align:center;padding:20px&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;/public/images/blog/exhibit/exhibit_main.png&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After watching the video, the visitor can pick between 2 interactive case studies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;text-align:center;padding:20px&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;/public/images/blog/exhibit/exhibit_cases.png&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here the visitor is presented with a medical case that utilizes personalized medicine to treat the patient.  Through a guided tour, the visitor is shown the variants in genes known to contribute to a medical condition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;text-align:center;padding:20px&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;/public/images/blog/exhibit/exhibit_screening.png&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One case study focuses on looking for a harmful variant that runs in a family that has a history of colon cancer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;text-align:center;padding:20px&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;/public/images/blog/exhibit/exhibit_screening_image2.png&quot; style=&quot;width:40%&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;/public/images/blog/exhibit/exhibit_screening_image1.png&quot; style=&quot;width:40%&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other focuses on proper dosage of a medicine prescribed for atrial fibrillation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;text-align:center;padding:20px&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;/public/images/blog/exhibit/exhibit_genotypes.png&quot; style=&quot;width:70%&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We use the case studies to introduce important concepts like genotypes, gene transcripts, gene annotations, and variant prioritization.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our lab gained a real appreciation for the work involved in creating an interactive exhibit.  We relied heavily on the Natural History museum's expertise on how to best present scientific ideas to the museum visitors to keep them engaged.  It was a challenge to keep the case studies realistic yet simple enough to convey the basic concepts.  One of the best perks was getting a personalized tour through the museum.  We all walked away thinking, 'Man, I love my job'.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During last week's opening night of the exhibit, it was rewarding to see the public's interest in genomics and how doctors and researchers can benefit from our tools.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A big thanks goes out to Tony Di Sera for modifying gene.iobio for use in the exhibit and creating the content for the main video and case studies,  Alistair Ward for doing the voice recordings and creating the data and script for the guided tours, Yi Qiao for turning our IOBIO backend services into an offline, self-contained server, Mary Anne Karren, Lisa Thompson, and Gabor Marth for their support and contribution throughout this project.  Also, Brett Thompson from &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.pixelcrane.com/&quot;&gt;Pixelcrane&lt;/a&gt; did an outstanding job on the video and all of the animations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We plan on utilizing much of this work for upcoming training and public outreach events.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Taxonomer.iobio</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2016/05/26/taxonomer.iobio/"/>
   <updated>2016-05-26T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2016/05/26/taxonomer.iobio</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;We are pleased to release a new, unique web app, &lt;a href=&quot;http://taxonomer.iobio.io&quot;&gt;taxonomer.iobio&lt;/a&gt;, for real-time interactive analysis of metagenomic data, based on the methods published today in a &lt;a href=&quot;http://genomebiology.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/s13059-016-0969-1&quot;&gt;paper in Genome Biology&lt;/a&gt;. Taxonomer.iobio is the result of what has been a really fun and productive collaboration between the Taxonomer team (the laboratories of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.yandell-lab.org/&quot;&gt;Mark Yandell&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://healthcare.utah.edu/fad/mddetail.php?physicianID=u0533994&quot;&gt;Robert Schlaberg&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;http://eilbeck_lab.topaz.genetics.utah.edu/&quot;&gt;Karen Eilbeck&lt;/a&gt;)  developing a super fast and accurate taxonomic DNA read classification software, and the iobio team in the laboratory of &lt;a href=&quot;http://marthlab.org/&quot;&gt;Gabor Marth&lt;/a&gt; turning it into an intuitive and interactive web analysis tool. Taxonomer has a very wide application area, including clinical diagnostics (see press release from the ARUP Reference Diagnostic Laboratory). Here we focus on the web app that can be used as a &quot;microscope&quot; for essentially all types of DNA or RNA sequencing datasets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a nutshell, users of this tool need to specify (but not upload!) a FASTA or FASTQ format sequence file containing either RNA-Seq gene expression data or the output of a DNA sequencing experiment. &lt;a href=&quot;http://taxonomer.iobio.io&quot;&gt;Taxonmer.iobio&lt;/a&gt; streams the first several thousand sequencing reads to Taxonomer which quickly classifies the reads, and returns the results to the analysis app where it is visualized. It should only take a few seconds to see the gross biological composition of your data, after which you can dig down into each kingdom (e.g. bacteria, viruses, fungi) to see higher-resolution classification, sometimes down to the species or even strain level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;intro&quot;&gt;Intro&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First a quick intro to the different parts of taxonomer.iobio.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;data-overview&quot;&gt;Data Overview&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Taxonomer analyzes the incoming read data in two steps: (1) a binner step, which is shown as a pie chart and (2) a classifier step, which is shown as a sunburst chart. The number of reads that are classified are shown in the data overview panel (red arrow below). More information regarding why some reads are not classified can be found in the &lt;a href=&quot;http://genomebiology.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/s13059-016-0969-1&quot;&gt;paper&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/public/images/blog/tax.iobio_data_overview.png&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;style&gt;
  span { padding: 1px 5px; color: white; }
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;binner-pie-chart&quot;&gt;Binner Pie Chart&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Taxonomer first quickly identifies each read as being in one of the following bins &lt;span style=&quot;background:#25aaff&quot;&gt;Human&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span style=&quot;background:#ff6f03&quot;&gt;Bacterial&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span style=&quot;background:purple&quot;&gt;Viral&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span style=&quot;background:red&quot;&gt;Phage&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span style=&quot;background:green&quot;&gt;Fungal&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span style=&quot;background:#06ac61&quot;&gt;PhiX&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span style=&quot;background:#5877ab&quot;&gt;Ambiguous&lt;/span&gt;, or &lt;span style=&quot;background:rgb(120,120,120)&quot;&gt;Unknown&lt;/span&gt;. Ambiguous is for reads that fit into 2 or more bins and unknown is for reads that do not fit into any bin. The pie chart below has two parts: (1) the traditional pie chart displays the binner information and (2) the outer edge of the pie chart (blue arrow) displays the subset of the binned reads that could be further classified. In the pie chart below only bacterial and viral reads could be further classified.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/public/images/blog/binner_pie_chart.png&quot; style=&quot;width:400px; margin:auto; display:block&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;classifier-sunburst&quot;&gt;Classifier Sunburst&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After binning, Taxonomer proceeds to more finely classify the reads. This could result in a read being classified into a particular phylum or even into a particular species, if sufficiently unique. For example, the Sunburst below goes from a broader classification of Bacteria Kingdom in the middle to a finer classification along the edges. Additionally, the size of each arc in the sunburst contains all the reads that classified to that specific arc and its children arcs. For example, the Class Alphaproteobacteria in the sunburst below contains all the reads that can be classified to the Alphaproteobacteria, regardless of whether those reads can be more finely classified (e.g. Order Rhizobiales).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/public/images/blog/taxonomer.iobio_release.png&quot; style=&quot;width:400px; margin:auto; display:block&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;a-few-good-features&quot;&gt;A few good features&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just a few things worth pointing out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;easy-sharing&quot;&gt;Easy sharing&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the nice things about working with data as URLs and public databases is that all analyses can be easily shared. Simply copy and paste the URL in the browser bar and the analysis can be shared with anyone! We think easy sharing is really important for open science, so try to include it in all our apps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;full-sra-and-ena-database-support&quot;&gt;Full SRA and ENA Database Support&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/sra&quot;&gt;SRA database&lt;/a&gt; can be accessed easily via their SRAtool kit, so we added support to analyze any sample as long as you know its SRR, DRR, or ERR accession id. This is a lot of fun when paired with cool datasets like the &lt;a href=&quot;http://trace.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/Traces/study/?acc=SRP051511&quot;&gt;Pathomap Project&lt;/a&gt;, which swabbed and sequenced a bunch of areas around the NYC Subway system. Here is a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/maps/@40.7757841,-73.9752183,3a,75y,169.38h,59.61t/data=!3m6!1e1!3m4!1sbQfa2C112y1j8KJtU8A6MQ!2e0!7i13312!8i6656!6m1!1e1&quot;&gt;bench in central park&lt;/a&gt; that you can &lt;a href=&quot;http://taxonomer.iobio.io/?sra=SRR1749235&quot;&gt;find some bacteria&lt;/a&gt; used in culturing mozzarella, so you know people are eating their lunch there! To see the bacteria you have to zoom into All -&amp;gt;Bacteria -&amp;gt;Firmicutes -&amp;gt;Bacilli -&amp;gt;Lactobacillales. Of course if you look at the viral sequence found on the same bench it may make you rethink if you would want to eat your lunch there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/public/images/blog/mozzarella.png&quot; style=&quot;width:400px; margin:auto; display:block&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also fully support &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ebi.ac.uk/ena&quot;&gt;ENA&lt;/a&gt;, the EBI Nuceotid Archive. Since &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ebi.ac.uk/ena/data/view/ERX979103&quot;&gt;ENA supplies http&lt;/a&gt; links to their raw fastq files, we can analyze ENA data without without any extra effort. And here's a human sequencing data sample and you can quickly see that there is a little contamination &lt;a href=&quot;http://taxonomer.iobio.io/?url=ftp://ftp.sra.ebi.ac.uk/vol1/fastq/ERR899/ERR899714/ERR899714_1.fastq.gz&quot;&gt;example in taxonomer.iobio&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Phenolyzer</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2016/03/30/phenolyzer/"/>
   <updated>2016-03-30T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2016/03/30/phenolyzer</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A &lt;a href=&quot;http://iobio.io/2016/03/28/multi-gene/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;previous post&lt;/a&gt; in the &lt;a href=&quot;http://gene.iobio.io&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;gene.iobio&lt;/a&gt; version 2 blog series focused on analyzing multiple genes simultaneously. This functionality has really increased the power of &lt;a href=&quot;http://gene.iobio.io&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;gene.iobio&lt;/a&gt;, making it a lot easier to analyze a set of genes and identify candidate disease variants. The problem is, though, that we still need to generate a list of genes to analyze. As described in the &lt;a href=&quot;http://iobio.io/2016/03/29/acmg56/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;previous post&lt;/a&gt;, we can start with the list of 56 genes identified by the ACMG, but what would be ideal, would be start with a phenotype and generate a gene list from there. Fortunately, that is exactly what we can do!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this post, we will use the modified &lt;a href=&quot;http://gene.iobio.io/?rel0=proband&amp;amp;rel1=mother&amp;amp;rel2=father&amp;amp;name0=&amp;amp;vcf0=https://s3.amazonaws.com/iobio/gene/wgs_platinum/platinum-trio.vcf.gz&amp;amp;bam0=https://s3.amazonaws.com/iobio/gene/wgs_platinum/NA12878.bam&amp;amp;name1=&amp;amp;vcf1=https://s3.amazonaws.com/iobio/gene/wgs_platinum/platinum-trio.vcf.gz&amp;amp;bam1=https://s3.amazonaws.com/iobio/gene/wgs_platinum/NA12892.bam&amp;amp;name2=&amp;amp;vcf2=https://s3.amazonaws.com/iobio/gene/wgs_platinum/platinum-trio.vcf.gz&amp;amp;bam2=https://s3.amazonaws.com/iobio/gene/wgs_platinum/NA12891.bam&amp;amp;sample0=NA12878&amp;amp;sample1=NA12891&amp;amp;sample2=NA12892&amp;amp;genes=RAI1&amp;amp;gene=RAI1&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Platinum trio&lt;/a&gt; dataset and assume this data originates from a family trio where the child is suffering from &lt;i&gt;lactic acidosis&lt;/i&gt;. If we know a lot about this phenotype, we may know of some likely genes where we can start our analysis, but what if we do not? Or what if these genes turn up no candidate variants? Using &lt;a href=&quot;http://phenolyzer.usc.edu/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Phenolyzer&lt;/a&gt;, a tool developed in the lab of &lt;a href=&quot;http://genomics.usc.edu/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Kai Wang&lt;/a&gt; at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.usc.edu/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;USC&lt;/a&gt;, we can use the phenotype to generate a gene list. For more information on this tool, or other software developed in this lab, go &lt;a href=&quot;http://genomics.usc.edu/research&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To use &lt;a href=&quot;http://phenolyzer.usc.edu/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Phenolyzer&lt;/a&gt;, click on the 'Genes' button to the left of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://gene.iobio.io&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;gene.iobio&lt;/a&gt; screen and then enter your phenotype terms where indicated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/public/images/blog/phenolyzer/phenolyzer.png&quot; style=&quot;width:55%; margin:20px 120px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this case, we enter &lt;i&gt;lactic acidosis&lt;/i&gt;, click 'Run' and wait for &lt;a href=&quot;http://phenolyzer.usc.edu/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Phenolyzer&lt;/a&gt; to do its magic! Very briefly, &lt;a href=&quot;http://phenolyzer.usc.edu/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Phenolyzer&lt;/a&gt; works by trying to match the entered phenotype terms to disease and phenotype terms in its own database to produce a list of seed genes. These genes are then checked for interactions with all other genes in the genome, accounting for four types of interaction; protein-protein interactions, genes in the same Biosystem or the same gene family and in transcription interactions. Based on all of this, a machine learning model is used to generate a score for each gene, and the output is a list of genes ordered by their scores.  The output gene list for &lt;i&gt;lactic acidosis&lt;/i&gt; appears in the left panel and the top 10 (this number is user configurable) genes appear as gene badges, ready to be interrogated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/public/images/blog/phenolyzer/phenolyzer-list.png&quot; style=&quot;width:100%; margin:20px 0px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By default, the genes are not automatically analyzed, but we can select 'Analyze all' to begin analysis. When complete, the gene badges describe any interesting variants within them using the glyphs described in the &lt;a href=&quot;http://iobio.io/2016/03/28/multi-gene/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;multi-gene analysis post&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/public/images/blog/phenolyzer/gene-badges.png&quot; style=&quot;width:100%; margin:20px 0px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The gene badges are in the prioritized order, so the gene to the furthest left (TTPA) is considered the most important by &lt;a href=&quot;http://phenolyzer.usc.edu/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Phenolyzer&lt;/a&gt;. The RAI1 gene still appears in the gene badges, since this was present prior to running Phenolyzer. We can see that there are no glyphs associated with the TTPA gene, so there are no high impact variants to look at there. The highest ranked gene that does have interesting variants to look at is PDHA1, so that is the first gene we should look at. In this gene, we see only two variants; an insertion in a promoter and a &lt;i&gt;de novo&lt;/i&gt; missense variant predicted to be &lt;i&gt;deleterious&lt;/i&gt; by SIFT and &lt;i&gt;probably_damaging&lt;/i&gt; by PolyPhen. The variant is not seen in either 1000 Genomes or in ExAC, so this variant may well be a good candidate for the obseved phenotype.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/public/images/blog/phenolyzer/pdha1.png&quot; style=&quot;width:75%; margin:20px 100px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We hope that you find this functionality useful and we would like to thank Kai Wang and his lab for allowing &lt;a href=&quot;http://phenolyzer.usc.edu/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Phenolyzer&lt;/a&gt; to be integrated into &lt;a href=&quot;http://gene.iobio.io&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;gene.iobio&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>ACMG 56 genes</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2016/03/29/acmg56/"/>
   <updated>2016-03-29T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2016/03/29/acmg56</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;In March 2013, an &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.acmg.net/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;The American College of Medical Genetics and Genomics (ACMG)&lt;/a&gt; working group released a list of 57 genes (later revised to 56), that harbour mutations that when identified, could lead to severe outcomes, but were medically actionable. These genes are implicated in a number of disorders, including inherited cancers, inherited cardiac diseases, connective tissue diseases affecting the cardiovascular system, familial hypercholesterolemia, and malignant hyperthermia susceptibility. The ACMG also generated a list of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/23788249&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;recommendations&lt;/a&gt; that state that known pathogenic (or in some cases expected pathogenic) variants discovered in any of these genes should be reported regardless of an individuals age. These recommendations referred to what are now known as secondary findings in an individual undergoing exome or genome sequencing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was felt that ethical concerns around testing minors for secondary findings was compensated by the potential benefit to the future health of the individual and their family. As such, the working group did not support an option to allow an opt-out of receiving this information, however, in &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nature.com/gim/journal/v17/n1/full/gim2014151a.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;March 2014&lt;/a&gt;, the recommendations were relaxed to allow an opt-out. It was then recommended that individuals undergoing exome or genome sequencing should undergo counseling before and after testing. Annual updates to the ACMG policy on secondary findings is expected as sequencing becomes more ubiquitous and our ability to interpret findings improves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The importance of these genes is clear, and it is likely that when analyzing an individual or a family in &lt;a href=&quot;http://gene.iobio.io&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;gene.iobio&lt;/a&gt;, looking at variants in them will be desirable. To make this an easy task for the user, we have made the ACMG56 genes a default list that can be easily selected for analysis. If we open up &lt;a href=&quot;http://gene.iobio.io/?rel0=proband&amp;amp;rel1=mother&amp;amp;rel2=father&amp;amp;name0=NA19240&amp;amp;vcf0=https://s3.amazonaws.com/iobio/gene/wes_1000g/exome-trio.vcf.gz&amp;amp;bam0=https://s3.amazonaws.com/iobio/gene/wes_1000g/NA19240.bam&amp;amp;sample0=NA19240&amp;amp;name1=NA19238&amp;amp;vcf1=https://s3.amazonaws.com/iobio/gene/wes_1000g/exome-trio.vcf.gz&amp;amp;bam1=https://s3.amazonaws.com/iobio/gene/wes_1000g/NA19238.bam&amp;amp;sample1=NA19238&amp;amp;name2=NA19239&amp;amp;vcf2=https://s3.amazonaws.com/iobio/gene/wes_1000g/exome-trio.vcf.gz&amp;amp;bam2=https://s3.amazonaws.com/iobio/gene/wes_1000g/NA19239.bam&amp;amp;sample2=NA19239&amp;amp;gene=RAI1&amp;amp;genes=RAI1,AIRE,PDGFB,MYLK2,PDHA1&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;gene.iobio&lt;/a&gt; with the modified 1000 Genomes exome trio dataset loaded, click on 'Genes' at the left of the screen, we can then select 'Import ACMG56 Genes'.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/public/images/blog/acmg56/select.png&quot; style=&quot;width:55%; margin:20px 250px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once selected, the ACMG56 genes replace all other genes that were being analyzed and appear as gene badges (as discussed in the &lt;a href=&quot;http://127.0.0.1:4001/2016/03/28/multi-gene/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;previous post&lt;/a&gt;). If we then select 'Analyze all', each of the genes is analyzed in turn. By clicking on the gene badge, we can quickly jump to any of the analyzed genes and assess the contained variants, while processing continues through the list. If we perform the analysis on the ACMG56 genes for this modified exome trio dataset, we see the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/public/images/blog/acmg56/genes.png&quot; style=&quot;width:100%; margin:20px 0px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With almost no effort on our part, we have scanned for secondary findings in this individual. The results suggest that we should take a closer look at BRCA2, APC, MYBPC3, TMEM43, SCN5A, PCSK9 and CACNA1S. If we take a look in the APC gene, for example, we can see that the child has a heterozygous missense variant inherited from her mother that is listed as of uncertain significance in ClinVar, but is predicted to be possibly_damaging by PolyPhen. The variant has very low allele frequency in the 1000 Genomes data (0.02%) and is not seen in ExAC.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/public/images/blog/acmg56/APC.png&quot; style=&quot;width:70%; margin:20px 100px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Being able to quickly analyze the ACMG56 genes gives a quick and easy way to analyze the proband in a set of genes known to be implicated in a number of diseases and have potentially actionable outcomes. This is an extremely powerful feature which we really hope the community finds useful.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Multi gene analysis</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2016/03/28/multi-gene/"/>
   <updated>2016-03-28T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2016/03/28/multi-gene</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;http://gene.iobio.io&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;gene.iobio&lt;/a&gt; version 2 blog series marches on with a discussion of multi-gene analysis. We think this is a major advancement and takes &lt;a href=&quot;http://gene.iobio.io&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;gene.iobio&lt;/a&gt; from a cool way of visualizing integrated data in a single gene, to a powerful method of performing analysis across sets of relevant genes. A following post in the series will look at generating gene lists based on phenotype using &lt;a href=&quot;http://phenolyzer.usc.edu/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Phenolyzer&lt;/a&gt;, which really helps direct analysis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To demonstrate functionality, we will look at the &lt;a href=&quot;http://127.0.0.1:4000/?rel0=proband&amp;amp;rel1=mother&amp;amp;rel2=father&amp;amp;name0=&amp;amp;vcf0=https://s3.amazonaws.com/iobio/gene/wgs_platinum/platinum-trio.vcf.gz&amp;amp;bam0=https://s3.amazonaws.com/iobio/gene/wgs_platinum/NA12878.bam&amp;amp;name1=&amp;amp;vcf1=https://s3.amazonaws.com/iobio/gene/wgs_platinum/platinum-trio.vcf.gz&amp;amp;bam1=https://s3.amazonaws.com/iobio/gene/wgs_platinum/NA12892.bam&amp;amp;name2=&amp;amp;vcf2=https://s3.amazonaws.com/iobio/gene/wgs_platinum/platinum-trio.vcf.gz&amp;amp;bam2=https://s3.amazonaws.com/iobio/gene/wgs_platinum/NA12891.bam&amp;amp;sample0=NA12878&amp;amp;sample1=NA12891&amp;amp;sample2=NA12892&amp;amp;genes=RAI1&amp;amp;gene=RAI1&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;RAI1&lt;/a&gt; usecase. Here we see a familiar view of the Platinum trio data, which we can interrogate as we see fit. But what if we are interested in looking at variants in a different gene? We can add another gene, say AIRE, using the gene entry box at the top of the screen. Now we see both genes have a &lt;i&gt;badge&lt;/i&gt; below the gene entry box, with a raft of glyphs in them, as shown below:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/public/images/blog/multiple-genes/gene-badges.png&quot; style=&quot;width:75%; margin:20px 100px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what does all this mean? Here are some details about these gene badges and how to use them:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Clicking on a gene badge will take you to that gene,&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If any interesting variants are present in the gene, the glyphs indicate what. In the RAI1 gene, they indicate there is a least one variant (each glyph can be referring to a different variant) in the gene that is:&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;a high impact variant, as predicted by VEP (&lt;img src=&quot;/public/images/blog/multiple-genes/high-impact.png&quot; style=&quot;width:2%; margin:-2px 0px;&quot; /&gt;),&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;a pathogenic variant in ClinVar (&lt;img src=&quot;/public/images/blog/multiple-genes/clinvar.png&quot; style=&quot;width:2%; margin:0px 0px;&quot; /&gt;),&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;a &lt;i&gt;de novo&lt;/i&gt; variant (&lt;img src=&quot;/public/images/blog/multiple-genes/denovo.png&quot; style=&quot;width:2%; margin:-2px 0px;&quot; /&gt;),&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;a recessive variant (&lt;img src=&quot;/public/images/blog/multiple-genes/recessive.png&quot; style=&quot;width:2%; margin:-2px 0px;&quot; /&gt;).&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If the checkmark (&lt;img src=&quot;/public/images/blog/multiple-genes/checkmark.png&quot; style=&quot;width:2%; margin:0px 0px;&quot; /&gt;) is present at the left of the gene badge, this indicates that the gene has been analyzed. The other glyphs will only be present if the gene has been analyzed, so this checkmark can differentiate between the case where the gene has been analyzed, but there are no interesting variants in the gene (&lt;img src=&quot;/public/images/blog/multiple-genes/analyzed.png&quot; style=&quot;width:10%; margin:-5px 0px;&quot; /&gt;), or that analysis on the gene has yet to be performed (&lt;img src=&quot;/public/images/blog/multiple-genes/not_analyzed.png&quot; style=&quot;width:8%; margin:-5px 0px;&quot; /&gt;), so we need to analyze the gene to determine if interesting variants are present.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Hovering over the HPO gene-to-phenotype glyph (&lt;img src=&quot;/public/images/blog/multiple-genes/gene-pheno-glyph.png&quot; style=&quot;width:2%; margin:-2px 0px;&quot; /&gt;), when present, provides information on gene associated phenotypes. For example, these are the phenotypes associated with the RAI gene:&lt;/li&gt;

  &lt;div&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/public/images/blog/multiple-genes/gene-pheno.png&quot; style=&quot;width:100%; margin:20px 0px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These gene badges make it simple to jump around a set of genes, analyzing data and identifying potentially interesting variants within them. An important question you might ask is how do we define a list of genes to look at? We can add each gene one by one, but we might want to look at a set of genes that we know are associated with a disease, or are the output of gene prioritization software. The next but one post will discuss using &lt;a href=&quot;http://phenolyzer.usc.edu/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Phenolyzer&lt;/a&gt; to generate a gene list, but here we will touch on two simple methods.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;import-a-gene-list&quot;&gt;Import a gene list&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the left panel, we can click the 'Genes' button to bring up a menu that lets us define gene lists. The 'Import Gene set' dropdown provides a space where we can manually import or paste a comma separated list of genes. Pressing 'Done' will prompt &lt;a href=&quot;http://gene.iobio.io&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;gene.iobio&lt;/a&gt; to add all defined genes as badges in the top panel so we can start working with them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/public/images/blog/multiple-genes/gene-import.png&quot; style=&quot;width:75%; margin:20px 0px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;analyze-the-acmg56-genes&quot;&gt;Analyze the ACMG56 genes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.acmg.net/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;The American College of Medical Genetics and Genomics (ACMG)&lt;/a&gt; has defined a list of 56 genes that have been implicated predominantly in cancer and cardiovascular disease risk. It can be good practice to look for any known pathogenic variants in these genes, so you can add them by clicking the 'Import ACMG56 Genes' button. By clicking this, all 56 genes will be added to the top panel and be ready for analysis. The next post in the series will give a brief discussion of ths feature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;analyze-all-genes&quot;&gt;Analyze all genes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once a set of genes has been defined, the next step is usually to see if any of them harbour potentially interesting variants. Preferably, we would like to achieve this without having to click through every gene individiually. Luckily, we are not forced to do that! Instead, we can just click 'Analyze all' to the left of the gene badges and each gene will be analyzed in turn; the gene being analyzed has a working symbol (&lt;img src=&quot;/public/images/blog/multiple-genes/working.png&quot; style=&quot;width:2%; margin:-2px 0px;&quot; /&gt;) to identify which gene is being processed. As each gene is analyzed the check mark (&lt;img src=&quot;/public/images/blog/multiple-genes/checkmark.png&quot; style=&quot;width:2%; margin:0px 0px;&quot; /&gt;) appears along with any glyphs describing contained variants. Once complete, the glyphs appearing in each gene badge direct us to where interesting variants lie (note that you can click on an analyzed gene to investigate, while &lt;a href=&quot;http://gene.iobio.io&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;gene.iobio&lt;/a&gt; continues to work through the rest of the genes).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As always, &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:iobioproject@gmail.com&quot; subject=&quot;gene.iobio suggestions&quot;&gt;contact us&lt;/a&gt; with any questions or comments, and stay tuned for the next two posts describing using the ACMG56 genes and the use of &lt;a href=&quot;http://phenolyzer.usc.edu/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Phenolyzer&lt;/a&gt; to turn your phenotype into a prioritized gene list.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>GENCODE or RefSeq?</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2016/03/21/gene-sets/"/>
   <updated>2016-03-21T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2016/03/21/gene-sets</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Continuing the blog series accompanying the &lt;a href=&quot;http://gene.iobio.io&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;gene.iobio&lt;/a&gt; version 2 release, we will discuss how to choose between the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.gencodegenes.org&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;GENCODE&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/RefSeq&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;RefSeq&lt;/a&gt; transcript sets and then different gene transcripts within each set. There are a lot of interesting discussions on the effects of using one or the other gene set. For example, this &lt;a href=&quot;http://bmcgenomics.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/1471-2164-16-S8-S2&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;paper&lt;/a&gt; has a more detailed discussion on the two sets, and this &lt;a href=&quot;http://genomemedicine.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/gm543&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;paper&lt;/a&gt; discusses the differences between functional annotations achieved using different software and transcripts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-do-i-select-a-set&quot;&gt;How do I select a set?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before looking into some details about the two gene sets, let's first see how to choose which gene set to use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/public/images/blog/gene-sets/selector.png&quot; style=&quot;width:100%; margin:20px 0px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Click the gene set selector wheel to select between the GENCODE and the RefSeq sets and then use the transcript selector to select the desired transcript.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/public/images/blog/gene-sets/selectors.png&quot; style=&quot;width:100%; margin:20px 0px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It's that easy! When you change to a different transcript, &lt;a href=&quot;http://gene.iobio.io&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;gene.iobio&lt;/a&gt; will reannotate all of the gene variants based on the new transcript. Depending on how different the transcripts are, this can lead to big changes. For example, the &lt;a href=&quot;http://gene.iobio.io/usecases.html#PDGFB&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;PDGFB&lt;/a&gt; usecase shows the example of an intronic variant in one transcript being reannotated as a high-impact frameshift mutation in a different transcript.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;some-details-about-the-two-gene-sets&quot;&gt;Some details about the two gene sets&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;i&gt;GENCODE gene set&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol type=&quot;1&quot;&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The GENCODE consortium was set up to provide reference gene annotations for the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.genome.gov/ENCODE&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;ENCODE&lt;/a&gt; project,&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Aims to be comprehensive, e.g. include pseudogenes, long non-coding RNAs (lncRNAs), short RNAs as well as protein-coding transcripts,&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Includes extensive manual annotation by the HAVANA group, as well as computational annotation. Approximately &lt;a href=&quot;http://bmcgenomics.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/1471-2164-16-S8-S2&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;93.4%&lt;/a&gt; of the annotations involve manual annotation,&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Is undergoing constant validation by many groups in the consortium,&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Is the default annotation set used by the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ensembl.org&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Ensembl&lt;/a&gt; project.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;refseq-gene-set&quot;&gt;RefSeq gene set&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol type=&quot;1&quot;&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Widely used gene set produced by the &lt;a href=&quot;&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;NCBI&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Has significant manually annotated content, but much less than GENCODE (&lt;a href=&quot;http://bmcgenomics.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/1471-2164-16-S8-S2&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;~45%&lt;/a&gt; of transcripts are listed as MODEL),&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Transcripts are named as:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;NM: Manually curated, protein-coding transcripts,&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;NR: Non-coding transcrips,&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;XM: Predicted protein-coding models.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As an example, the available GENCODE and RefSeq transcripts for the BRCA1 gene are shown below. GENCODE clearly has many more available transcripts for this gene. Also, you can see that both gene sets provide the corresponding ID from the other set to the right of the transcript where applicable. The canonical transcript (that picked by default in &lt;a href=&quot;http://gene.iobio.io&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;gene.iobio&lt;/a&gt;) is the same in both gene sets (you can see that the GENCODE transcript gives the ID of the canonical RefSeq transcript and vice versa), although the GENCODE transcript includes UTRs, where RefSeq does not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/public/images/blog/gene-sets/BRCA1-transcripts.png&quot; style=&quot;width:100%; margin:20px 0px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;so-which-set-should-i-use&quot;&gt;So which set should I use?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It may be that the your lab uses a particular set of transcripts and has good reason for the choice, so it is probably a good idea to use what your lab/collaborators use. If you want to see more transcript options (including, e.g. pseudogenes), GENCODE would be the better choice for you. In the absense of additional information, we recommend using the canonical transcript.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>What is the filter status in gene.iobio?</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2016/03/16/filter-status/"/>
   <updated>2016-03-16T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2016/03/16/filter-status</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This is the second in a &lt;a href=&quot;http://iobio.io/2016/03/14/gene-version2/index.html#v2posts&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;series of blog posts&lt;/a&gt; describing updates in the version 2.0 release of &lt;a href=&quot;http://gene.iobio.io&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;gene.iobio&lt;/a&gt;. In this post, we discuss the concept of &lt;strong&gt;&lt;i&gt;filter status&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; and how to display the variants you want to see. If we open the example &lt;a href=&quot;http://gene.iobio.io/?rel0=proband&amp;amp;rel1=mother&amp;amp;rel2=father&amp;amp;name0=&amp;amp;vcf0=https://s3.amazonaws.com/iobio/gene/wgs_platinum/NA12878.platinum.vcf.gz&amp;amp;affectedSibs=&amp;amp;unaffectedSibs=&amp;amp;genes=&amp;amp;gene=BRCA1&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;data set&lt;/a&gt;, click on the 'Filter' button to the left, you will see the 'Filter status' at the top of the left panel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/public/images/blog/filter_status/filter_status.png&quot; style=&quot;width:25%; margin:20px 300px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First of all, what is the filter status anyway? The VCF file was likely generated using variant calling software, for example, &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/ekg/freebayes&quot;&gt;Freebayes&lt;/a&gt;, then post-processed with a number of tools. One task that may well have been performed is filtering, where a set of filters are set (e.g. quality has to be greater than 1, or the depth at the locus has to be greater than 10 etc.) and each variant is tested against these filters. Rather than throwing away variants that fail filters, the usual practice is to tag the variants with the result of the filtering. If the variant passed, it is often tagged with the value 'PASS'. If not, it is sometimes given a value based on the filter it failed, e.g. 'DEPTH&amp;lt;10'. If the variant failed multiple filters, it can have multiple values separated by a comma, e.g. DEPTH&amp;lt;10,QUAL&amp;lt;1. It is very common to see VCF files where passing variants are given the value 'PASS' and failing variants are not tagged at all. When no tag is given, the VCF field that stores the tag, has the value '.' set for the variant and so this is what we see in &lt;a href=&quot;http://gene.iobio.io&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;gene.iobio&lt;/a&gt;. Be careful with the '.' tag though, &lt;strong&gt;&lt;i&gt;it doesn't mean fail!&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; It just means no tag has been set, so if no filtering was performed on the VCF file, all variants will have the '.' tag. If 'PASS' is present for some variants and another variant has the filter status '.', it means fail only by the absense of 'PASS'!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As an example, the NA12878 Platinum variant &lt;a href=&quot;http://gene.iobio.io/?rel0=proband&amp;amp;rel1=mother&amp;amp;rel2=father&amp;amp;name0=&amp;amp;vcf0=https://s3.amazonaws.com/iobio/gene/wgs_platinum/NA12878.platinum.vcf.gz&amp;amp;affectedSibs=&amp;amp;unaffectedSibs=&amp;amp;genes=&amp;amp;gene=BRCA1&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;calls&lt;/a&gt; for BRCA1 are shown below:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/public/images/blog/filter_status/pass.png&quot; style=&quot;width:100%; margin: 20px 0&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First of all, we can see from the PROBAND variant card that there are 176 loaded variants in this gene, of which only 166 are displayed. The 'VCF Filter status' badge appearing next to these counts indicates that these variants have been removed because of their filter status. If we look in the 'Filter' panel at the left, we can see that there are a number of different tags. At the top is 'PASS' and &lt;a href=&quot;http://gene.iobio.io&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;gene.iobio&lt;/a&gt; is, by default, only displaying these variants. The remaining tags, OverlapConflict and SuspiciousHomAlt describe the filters failed by the other variants. If we deselect the 'PASS' variants and select the 'OverlapConflict' variants, we see the variants below:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/public/images/blog/filter_status/overlapConflict.png&quot; style=&quot;width:100%; margin: 20px 0&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are four overlapping deletions and four overlapping SNPs. In filtering this file, the software determined that multiple overlapping variants in a single sample is suspicious and tagged them with the OverlapConflict tag to suggest to us, that we should probably not use these variants, or at least use caution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By displaying only 'PASS' variants by default, &lt;a href=&quot;http://gene.iobio.io&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;gene.iobio&lt;/a&gt; omits these suspicious variants, so we don't waste our time analyzing them. But by giving you the option to display them, you can determine for yourself if you think the variants should be filtered out. But, we recommend you analyze your 'PASS' variants first!&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Gene.iobio version 2.0</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2016/03/14/gene-version2/"/>
   <updated>2016-03-14T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2016/03/14/gene-version2</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;We are thrilled to announce the release of &lt;a href=&quot;http://gene.iobio.io&quot;&gt;gene.iobio&lt;/a&gt; version 2.0! This new release features a major facelift and lots of new functionality that significantly enhances the power and usability of &lt;a href=&quot;http://gene.iobio.io&quot;&gt;gene.iobio&lt;/a&gt;. The single most important enhancement is that we have now moved from being a single gene to a multi-gene assessment tool, with integrated methods of generating and importing gene lists, including manual import and phenotype driven list generation with &lt;a href=&quot;http://phenolyzer.usc.edu&quot;&gt;Phenolyzer&lt;/a&gt;. Below, we can see where genes being investigated can be selected and the transcript set can be switched between Gencode and RefSeq.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/public/images/blog/gene_version2/badges.png&quot; style=&quot;width:100%; margin: 20px 0px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;v2posts&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
This post is the first in a series describing the new interface and features and will focus on changes to the interface. The series will then continue to address in more detail, the following topics:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol type=&quot;1&quot;&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://iobio.io/2016/03/16/filter-status/&quot;&gt;Displaying variants based on the VCF filter status&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Using RefSeq and GenCode gene transcripts,&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Analyzing multiple genes with &lt;a href=&quot;http://gene.iobio.io&quot;&gt;gene.iobio&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Analyzing the ACMG56 genes,&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Generating gene lists from phenotype terms using the &lt;a href=&quot;http://phenolyzer.usc.edu&quot;&gt;Phenolyzer&lt;/a&gt; tool from &lt;a href=&quot;http://genomics.usc.edu&quot;&gt;USC&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Bookmarking and exporting candidate variants,&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Importing candidate variants from e.g. GEMINI and interrogating with &lt;a href=&quot;http://gene.iobio.io&quot;&gt;gene.iobio&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Performing analysis with affected/unaffected siblings.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have included a series of menu buttons down the left hand side of the screen where all the analysis functionality is now accessible. When a button is selected, a panel is opened containing all the actions or information associated with the selected function. We will not discuss all of the buttons in this post (they will all be covered in the remainder of this series), but will demonstrate one of the panels. The image below shows the tutorial &lt;a href=&quot;http://gene.iobio.io/?rel0=proband&amp;amp;rel1=mother&amp;amp;rel2=father&amp;amp;name0=&amp;amp;vcf0=https://s3.amazonaws.com/iobio/gene/wgs_platinum/platinum-trio.vcf.gz&amp;amp;bam0=https://s3.amazonaws.com/iobio/gene/wgs_platinum/NA12878.bam&amp;amp;name1=&amp;amp;vcf1=https://s3.amazonaws.com/iobio/gene/wgs_platinum/platinum-trio.vcf.gz&amp;amp;bam1=https://s3.amazonaws.com/iobio/gene/wgs_platinum/NA12892.bam&amp;amp;name2=&amp;amp;vcf2=https://s3.amazonaws.com/iobio/gene/wgs_platinum/platinum-trio.vcf.gz&amp;amp;bam2=https://s3.amazonaws.com/iobio/gene/wgs_platinum/NA12891.bam&amp;amp;sample0=NA12878&amp;amp;sample1=NA12891&amp;amp;sample2=NA12892&amp;amp;genes=&amp;amp;gene=RAI1&quot; target=&quot;_app&quot;&gt;usecase&lt;/a&gt; for the RAI1 gene.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/public/images/blog/gene_version2/inspect.png&quot; style=&quot;width:100%; margin: 20px 0&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we mouse over a variant in the proband card, a tooltip appears with limited details about the variant. We have included in this tooltip the allele counts for the reference, alternate and other alleles (in the event of a sample showing more than two alleles due to e.g. error, mosaicism etc.) for all samples. The called zygosity for each of the samples is included next to the counts, so it is really easy to compare the calls across the family. If we want to know more details, click the variant and the left panel immediately jumps to 'Inspect' and is populated with additional details about the variant, including, where applicable, links out to ClinVar, NCBIs dbSNP database etc. We will be continuing to add more information to this panel as time goes by and will strive to address any of your &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:iobioproject@gmail.com&quot; subject=&quot;gene.iobio suggestions&quot;&gt;suggestions or comments&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We recommend trying out all the new features for yourself, including the powerful new &lt;a href=&quot;http://phenolyzer.usc.edu&quot;&gt;Phenolyzer&lt;/a&gt; tool, accessible by clicking the 'Genes' button and entering a phenotype, for example, 'lactic acidosis'. All the new features will be discussed in this blog series that we will be releasing regularly over the coming weeks. Remember, you can still access all resources, including &lt;a href=&quot;http://gene.iobio.io&quot;&gt;gene.iobio&lt;/a&gt; tours, tutorial use cases, screencasts, blogs etc. by clicking the 'About' button.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>ICGC Data Portal</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2015/12/08/icgc/"/>
   <updated>2015-12-08T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2015/12/08/icgc</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Vincent Ferretti and his team (I was in contact with Douglas Wong, Bob Tiernay, and Dusan Andric, but others may have worked on it too!) over at the Ontario Institute for Cancer Research have recently integrated bam.iobio into their really awesome data portal &lt;a href=&quot;https://dcc.icgc.org/repositories/files/FI9974&quot;&gt;see it here&lt;/a&gt;. The data portal pulls together data from many groups that are part of the International Cancer Genome Consortium (ICGC), giving a single nice interface to the data while also adding a lot of useful metrics. It's a very impressive effort and is loaded with great ways to better make sense of a large and diverse data set. I especially like the &lt;a href=&quot;https://dcc.icgc.org/search&quot;&gt;search page&lt;/a&gt; (image below), which gives some nice pie charts on project-level data metrics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/public/images/blog/icgc_search.png&quot; style=&quot;width:100%; margin: 20px 0&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a data portal, this project is faced with the challenge of working with remote data sitting in many different locations. It's really interesting to see how well iobio works with this architecture. Since iobio remotely samples data files, the  ICGC data portal can analyze and visualize this remote data without any downloading or major processing, which would probably require some complex backend code. Another perk is that all samples are instantly able to be visualized as soon as a member organization uploads some data, since it's happening in real-time.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>IOBIO Page views</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2015/09/29/iobio-pageview/"/>
   <updated>2015-09-29T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2015/09/29/iobio-pageview</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Last night I decided to take a look at the site analytics for all the iobio web sites over the last 6 months. I’ve been getting a lot more emails lately - both good (collaboration inquiries) and bad (bug reports!) - so I figured that the usage must be up. And it is. Things have really taken off in the last several months and we are getting consistent growth in users as shown by the chart above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;margin-top: 20px;&quot;&gt;
	One more interesting thing I found in google analytics was an animation showing the amount of new users (blue ball) and returning users  (green ball) and the amount of time they spend on the site over the last 6 months. 
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/public/images/blog/newVsReturning.gif&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;&amp;lt;div&amp;gt;
	You can see that the returning users spend more time on the site, which is not surprising since they are coming back to use it with a purpose. Also you can see that with the huge influx of new users, we are getting a steady growth of returning users. So it seems that a good percentage of people are sticking around.
&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;margin-top: 20px;&quot;&gt;
	All in all we are really excited about the community response to IOBIO and are working hard on some new apps and getting out the alpha release of the dev kit!
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Latest Exome sequencing in gene.iobio</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2015/09/29/gene-iobio-exome-seq/"/>
   <updated>2015-09-29T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2015/09/29/gene-iobio-exome-seq</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Exome data has unique characteristics, which affects the way the data is checked and analyzed. In this post, we will use exome data from a 1000 Genomes project trio to highlight some iobio features that are particularly useful when analyzing exome data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first step in the analysis is to ensure that the data quality is sufficiently high. We use bam.iobio to check the global statistics of the alignment files, which we can view &lt;a href=&quot;http://bam.iobio.io/?bam=https://s3.amazonaws.com/iobio/1000gSV/NA19238.mapped.ILLUMINA.bwa.YRI.exome.20130415.bam&amp;amp;region=1&quot; target=&quot;_new&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;text-align:center&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;/public/images/blog/bam_iobio_exome_data.png&quot; style=&quot;width:80%&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A noticeable problem with this view for exome alignments is that since the majority of the genome has zero coverage, the read coverage chart is dominated by the zero coverage bases. To focus on the exome only, we can select the ‘Default Bed’ option (highlighted in the above plot) to use the 1000 Genomes human exome targets file to focus sampling in these regions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;text-align:center&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;/public/images/blog/bam_iobio_exome_data_coverage_w_bed.png&quot; style=&quot;width:70%&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When only considering the targeted exome, the coverage is encouragingly generally greater than 60X.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, we want to look at the alignments and the variant calls for the trio. We will look at a few different genes, beginning with &lt;a href=&quot;http://gene.iobio.io/?rel0=proband&amp;amp;rel1=mother&amp;amp;rel2=father&amp;amp;gene=BRCA2&amp;amp;name0=NA19240&amp;amp;bam0=https://s3.amazonaws.com/iobio/1000gSV/NA19240.mapped.ILLUMINA.bwa.YRI.exome.20130415.bam&amp;amp;name1=NA19238&amp;amp;bam1=https://s3.amazonaws.com/iobio/1000gSV/NA19238.mapped.ILLUMINA.bwa.YRI.exome.20130415.bam&amp;amp;name2=NA19239&amp;amp;bam2=https://s3.amazonaws.com/iobio/1000gSV/NA19239.mapped.ILLUMINA.bwa.YRI.exome.20130415.bam&amp;amp;vcf0=https://s3.amazonaws.com/iobio/1000gSV/exome-trio.vcf.gz&amp;amp;sample0=NA19240&amp;amp;vcf1=https://s3.amazonaws.com/iobio/1000gSV/exome-trio.vcf.gz&amp;amp;sample1=NA19238&amp;amp;vcf2=https://s3.amazonaws.com/iobio/1000gSV/exome-trio.vcf.gz&amp;amp;sample2=NA19239&quot; target=&quot;_new&quot;&gt;BRCA2&lt;/a&gt;. We know that the 1000 Genomes samples were over 18 years of age and healthy at the time of DNA collection, but we can see that the father is carrying a heterozygous variant identified as possibly damaging by PolyPhen and deleterious by Sift in one of the exons. Snpeff identifies this variant as having a moderate impact and we can also see that the child (identified as the proband in this trio) has inherited this allele from her father. This variant appears as the highest ranked in the ‘Rank Variants’ table.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;text-align:center&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;/public/images/blog/gene_iobio_exome_data.png&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, let’s take a look at the &lt;a href=&quot;http://gene.iobio.io/?rel0=proband&amp;amp;rel1=mother&amp;amp;rel2=father&amp;amp;gene=CFTR&amp;amp;name0=NA19240&amp;amp;bam0=https://s3.amazonaws.com/iobio/1000gSV/NA19240.mapped.ILLUMINA.bwa.YRI.exome.20130415.bam&amp;amp;name1=NA19238&amp;amp;bam1=https://s3.amazonaws.com/iobio/1000gSV/NA19238.mapped.ILLUMINA.bwa.YRI.exome.20130415.bam&amp;amp;name2=NA19239&amp;amp;bam2=https://s3.amazonaws.com/iobio/1000gSV/NA19239.mapped.ILLUMINA.bwa.YRI.exome.20130415.bam&amp;amp;vcf0=https://s3.amazonaws.com/iobio/1000gSV/exome-trio.vcf.gz&amp;amp;sample0=NA19240&amp;amp;vcf1=https://s3.amazonaws.com/iobio/1000gSV/exome-trio.vcf.gz&amp;amp;sample1=NA19238&amp;amp;vcf2=https://s3.amazonaws.com/iobio/1000gSV/exome-trio.vcf.gz&amp;amp;sample2=NA19239&quot; target=&quot;_new&quot;&gt;CFTR gene&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;text-align:center&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;/public/images/blog/gene_iobio_exome_data_cftr.png&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we open gene.iobio in the CFTR gene, we are presented with the canonical transcript. We can immediately see that there is coverage in all three samples in what appears to be an intronic location. This situation is likely the result of an exon present in an alternative transcript for this gene. To check, we can use the ‘Transcript’ drop-down menu and look at all the other available transcripts. The processed transcript (i.e. a transcript that does not contain an open reading frame) highlighted in the figure below appears to have an exon in the location with coverage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;text-align:center&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;/public/images/blog/gene_iobio_transcript_menu_cftr.png&quot; style=&quot;width:60%&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When selected, we see that this coverage peak indeed fell within this exon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;text-align:center&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;/public/images/blog/gene_iobio_alt_transcript_cftr.png&quot; style=&quot;width:40%&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, we will look at the &lt;a href=&quot;http://gene.iobio.io/?rel0=proband&amp;amp;rel1=mother&amp;amp;rel2=father&amp;amp;gene=ABCB10&amp;amp;name0=NA19240&amp;amp;bam0=https://s3.amazonaws.com/iobio/1000gSV/NA19240.mapped.ILLUMINA.bwa.YRI.exome.20130415.bam&amp;amp;name1=NA19238&amp;amp;bam1=https://s3.amazonaws.com/iobio/1000gSV/NA19238.mapped.ILLUMINA.bwa.YRI.exome.20130415.bam&amp;amp;name2=NA19239&amp;amp;bam2=https://s3.amazonaws.com/iobio/1000gSV/NA19239.mapped.ILLUMINA.bwa.YRI.exome.20130415.bam&amp;amp;vcf0=https://s3.amazonaws.com/iobio/1000gSV/exome-trio.vcf.gz&amp;amp;sample0=NA19240&amp;amp;vcf1=https://s3.amazonaws.com/iobio/1000gSV/exome-trio.vcf.gz&amp;amp;sample1=NA19238&amp;amp;vcf2=https://s3.amazonaws.com/iobio/1000gSV/exome-trio.vcf.gz&amp;amp;sample2=NA19239&quot; target=&quot;_new&quot;&gt;ABCB10 gene&lt;/a&gt;.  This gene shows the opposite situation to what we observed in the CFTR gene. The final coding sequence (CDS) in the canonical transcript has no coverage in any of the samples. A quick check of the 1000 Genomes project exome targets bed file reveals that this exon is included and so coverage would be expected at this location. If it were the case that any of the samples harbored a deleterious mutation in this CDS, it would not be identified from this sequencing experiment, since no DNA sequence is present within it. This is a known cause of false negative variants, i.e. variants that are not called when they do exist and can quickly and easily be identified within gene.iobio.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;text-align:center&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;/public/images/blog/gene_iobio_exome_data_abcb10.png&quot; style=&quot;width:70%&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Latest Gene.iobio features</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2015/09/27/multisample-vcf-gene-iobio/"/>
   <updated>2015-09-27T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2015/09/27/multisample-vcf-gene-iobio</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The week, we have pushed out some new features in &lt;a href=&quot;http://gene.iobio.io&quot; target=&quot;_new&quot;&gt;gene.iobio&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;multi-sample-vcf-files&quot;&gt;Multi-sample VCF files&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We now support multi-sample VCF files.  After entering the VCF URL or selecting the VCF file, a dropdown will appear if the file contains multiple samples.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here we show a VCF file containing 100+ samples.  The sample list can be narrowed down using the type-ahead feature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;text-align:center&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;/public/images/blog/multisample_vcf.png&quot; style=&quot;width:40%&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is a screen capture showing a trio loaded from one file.  Even though the file might be quite large, gene.iobio only examines the samples of interest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;text-align:center&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;/public/images/blog/multisample_vcf_trio.png&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;secure-file-serving&quot;&gt;Secure File Serving&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gene.iobio can now handle files served using the https protocol, ensuring secure communication over the network – a requirement when analyzing sensitive data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;allele-counts&quot;&gt;Allele Counts&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hover over a variant and the tooltip will include a bar for allele counts.  In this example, you can see the allele counts for a trio.  Notice how the parents are heterogous alternates and the proband is homozygous alternate.  The allele counts verify that there is adequate sequence coverage to make these calls.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;text-align:center&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;/public/images/blog/allele_counts.png&quot; style=&quot;width:50%&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stay tuned.  More features are coming soon to gene.iobio including multi-gene navigation and extended trio functionality to analyze variants from unaffected siblings.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Gene.iobio integrates VEP</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2015/09/07/vep-in-gene-iobio/"/>
   <updated>2015-09-07T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2015/09/07/vep-in-gene-iobio</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;When we released &lt;a href=&quot;http://gene.iobio.io&quot; target=&quot;_new&quot;&gt;gene.iobio&lt;/a&gt; a couple weeks ago, we had a few requests to add Ensembl’s Variant Effect Predictor (VEP) tool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;tweet-feed&quot; style=&quot;padding-bottom:10px;&quot;&gt;
	&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;It will in a new release soon! &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/jxchong&quot;&gt;@jxchong&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/brent_p&quot;&gt;@brent_p&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Gabor Marth (@MarthGabor) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/MarthGabor/status/629013788931584000&quot;&gt;August 5, 2015&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
	&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And as any good PI does, Gabor was quick to sign us up to do it! After taking his Twitter account away, we made good on the promise and officially added VEP support, which gives us (along with SnpEff) two powerful variant effect predictor tools.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;vep-consequence&quot;&gt;VEP Consequence&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;VEP determines the variant consequence on protein coding, a classification that is analogous to SnpEff’s Effect. In fact, these classifications are highly concordant when evaluating coding variants, but keep in mind that these classifications do diverge in the categories of splicing, frameshift, and stop gain. &lt;a href=&quot;http://blog.goldenhelix.com/ajesaitis/the-sate-of-variant-annotation-a-comparison-of-annovar-snpeff-and-vep/&quot;&gt;Andrew Jesaitis has written a terrific blog post&lt;/a&gt; that explains these differences in his in depth comparison of SnpEff, VEP and Annovar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We only color variants with either SnpEff or VEP classifications at any given time. You can easily alternate between SnpEff and VEP classifications in the filter panel using the Impact dropdown.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;text-align:center&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;/public/images/blog/vepblog2.png&quot; style=&quot;width:20%&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, both classifications are visible on the variant tooltip displays.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;text-align:center&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;/public/images/blog/vepblog3.png&quot; style=&quot;width:50%&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By default, variants are colored based on SnpEff Impact, a high level prioritization scheme on SnpEff Effect, summarizing the categories into four possible levels:  High, Moderate, Modifier and Low.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;text-align:center&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;/public/images/blog/vepblog4.png&quot; style=&quot;width:15%;vertical-align:top&quot; /&gt;	
	&lt;img src=&quot;/public/images/blog/vepblog5.png&quot; style=&quot;width:80%&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To color based on SnpEff Effect, click on the Effect link.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/public/images/blog/vepblog6.png&quot; style=&quot;width:15%;vertical-align:top&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/public/images/blog/vepblog7.png&quot; style=&quot;width:80%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now the variants have switched from the SnpEff Impact color scheme (e.g. High, Moderate, Modifier, Low) to the SnpEff Effect color scheme (e.g. missense, frameshift, etc.).  The same color scheme switching can be performed on VEP impact and consequence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;predicting-impact-on-protein-function&quot;&gt;Predicting Impact on Protein Function&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given that non-synonymous SNPs comprise over half of the mutations known to be involved in human inherited diseases, algorithm-based approaches to predicting disruption to protein structure and function are critical to understanding human disease and phenotype &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC3572689/pdf/TSWJ2013-675851.pdf&quot;&gt;(Wu, Yang 2012)&lt;/a&gt;. VEP reports classifications from two such algorithms – &lt;a href=&quot;http://sift.jcvi.org/&quot;&gt;SIFT&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://genetics.bwh.harvard.edu/pph2/&quot;&gt;PolyPhen&lt;/a&gt;.  Both SIFT and PolyPhen analyze sequence homology, whereby substitutions at highly conserved regions are predicted to have higher impact on protein function.  In addition, PolyPhen utilizes sequence annotation to inventory features mapped to the location of the substitution.  PolyPhen also maps to the 3D protein structure to predict if the amino acid substitution will disrupt the hydrophobic core, alter electrostatic interactions, or interfere with ligand actions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gene.iobio provides filters based on SIFT and PolyPhen classifications:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;text-align:center&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;/public/images/blog/vepblog8.png&quot; style=&quot;width:20%;vertical-align:top&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;/public/images/blog/vepblog9.png&quot; style=&quot;width:25%;vertical-align:top&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition, PolyPhen and SIFT classifications are used to rank the variants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;text-align:center&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;/public/images/blog/vepblog10.png&quot; style=&quot;width:50%&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this example, the first variant in the ranked list has a PolyPhen classification of ‘Probably Damaging’ and a SIFT classification of ‘Deleterious’, providing additional insight into a moderate impact variant catalogued with conflicting interpretations in ClinVar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When evaluating a variant’s pathogenicity, it is important to consider the variation type and seek other evidence-based sources in addition to the SIFT and PolyPhen predictions.  In the paper by &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.researchgate.net/publication/45273588_Using_SIFT_and_PolyPhen_to_Predict_Loss-of-Function_and_Gain-of-Function_Mutations&quot;&gt;Flanagan, et al 2010&lt;/a&gt; which tested the predictive value of SIFT and PolyPhen, it was found that the sensitivity was reasonably high, but that the specificity was quite low, especially for gain-of-function mutations. When considering just SNPs or loss-of-function mutations, these tools performed much better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;regulatory-annotations&quot;&gt;Regulatory Annotations&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to annotating protein coding variants, VEP also reports on variants that are located in predicted regulatory sites based on the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ensembl.org/info/genome/funcgen/regulatory_build.html&quot;&gt;Ensembl Regulatory Build&lt;/a&gt;.  Gene.iobio now allows variant filtering on these regulatory classifications:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;text-align:center&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;/public/images/blog/vepblog11.png&quot; style=&quot;width:20%&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the variant tooltip provides link outs to Ensembl, showing multiple tracks for different cell types.  For example, SNP located in a predicted TF binding site is only active in the Human Embryonic Stem Cell type.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;text-align:center&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;/public/images/blog/vepblog12.png&quot; style=&quot;width:30%;vertical-align:top&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;/public/images/blog/vepblog13.png&quot; style=&quot;width:65%&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For TF motif features, the link out to Ensembl shows the sequence logo along with a frequency matrix from the JASPER core database &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed?Db=pubmed&amp;amp;Cmd=ShowDetailView&amp;amp;TermToSearch=14681366&amp;amp;ordinalpos=3&amp;amp;itool=EntrezSystem2.PEntrez.Pubmed.Pubmed_ResultsPanel.Pubmed_RVDocSum&quot;&gt;(Mathelier, et al 2013)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;text-align:center&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;/public/images/blog/vepblog14.png&quot; style=&quot;width:30%;vertical-align:top&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;/public/images/blog/vepblog15.png&quot; style=&quot;width:65%&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;variant-identifiers-and-nomenclature&quot;&gt;Variant Identifiers and Nomenclature&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;VEP also provides the dbSNP identifier (i.e. rs number) as well as the HGVS notation for the variant. The HGVS notation is based on the GENCODE transcript set. Additionally, we plan to incorporate the RefSeq transcript set in the near future.  In gene.iobio, the tooltip for the variant will show both HGVS notation and the dbSNP id, with the latter linking out to the dbSNP webpage for the particular variant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;text-align:center&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;/public/images/blog/vepblog16.png&quot; style=&quot;width:40%&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;coming-soon&quot;&gt;Coming Soon&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With VEP integration complete, stay tuned for enhancements to easily navigate through a set of genes, support for multi-sample vcfs, color exons based on sequence coverage, and much more.  (VEP is no longer planned!)&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Creating a compressed and indexed VCF</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2015/09/03/install-run-tabix/"/>
   <updated>2015-09-03T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2015/09/03/install-run-tabix</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Compressing VCF files with BGZip and indexing it with Tabix is the standard way VCF files are stored, and is the format that iobio apps support. The software to compress and index VCF files is called Tabix, developed by Heng Li at the Broad Institute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;for-macos-systems&quot;&gt;For MacOS systems&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We provide a simple Mac App for compressing and indexing vcf files using Tabix.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Download the &lt;a href=&quot;http://vcf.iobio.io/tabix/iTabixit.zip&quot;&gt;iTabixIt App&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Double-click to decompress it.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Download the &lt;a href=&quot;http://vcf.iobio.io/tabix/TabixBinary.zip&quot;&gt;Tabix and Bgzip binaries&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Double-click to decompress it in the same parent folder as the iTabixApp.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Now you should see an icon for the iTabixApp and a folder for the binaries.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;text-align:center&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;/public/images/blog/tabix1.png&quot; style=&quot;width:20%&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Now double-click on the iTabixIt icon to launch the app.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Select a .vcf file.  The app will start processing to compress and index the .vcf file.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;text-align:center&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;/public/images/blog/tabix2.png&quot; style=&quot;width:50%&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;When the app is down compressing and indexing the VCF file, green dots will appear next to the completed items.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;text-align:center&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;/public/images/blog/tabix3.png&quot; style=&quot;width:50%&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Now the .vcf.gz and .vcf.gz.tbi files will be created in the same directory as the .vcf file. Now you are ready to run vcf.iobio or gene.iobio, selecting these two files when prompted.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;for-linux-based-system&quot;&gt;For Linux-based system&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Download the latest tabix jar at &lt;a href=&quot;http://sourceforge.net/projects/samtools/files/tabix/&quot;&gt;http://sourceforge.net/projects/samtools/files/tabix/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Install C compiler and the ‘make’ utility with the package management system of your specific Linux distribution. In the case of Ubuntu, the following command should suffice:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;	$ sudo apt-get install build-essential
	$ tar -xjf tabix-0.2.6.tar.bz2
	$ cd tabix-0.2.6
	$ make
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Once you have successfully compiled Tabix (and bgzip), you can compress your vcf files with the following command:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;	$ /path/to/tabix/bgzip myvcf.vcf
	$ /path/to/tabix/tabix -p vcf myvcf.vcf.gz
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;These two commands will create two new files: the compressed vcf (.vcf.gz) and the index (.vcf.gz.tbi). Now you are ready to run vcf.iobio or gene.iobio, selecting these two files when prompted.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The manual page for Tabix and BGZip can be found at &lt;a href=&quot;http://samtools.sourceforge.net/tabix.shtml&quot;&gt;http://samtools.sourceforge.net/tabix.shtml&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>New app gene.iobio</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2015/08/04/gene.iobio_released/"/>
   <updated>2015-08-04T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2015/08/04/gene.iobio_released</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;We’ve been working on a new real-time interactive iobio analysis tool for the last few months and today are excited to officially release &lt;a href=&quot;http://gene.iobio.io&quot;&gt;gene.iobio&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;http://gene.iobio.io&quot;&gt;Gene.iobio&lt;/a&gt; is designed to help medical and clinical researchers hunt for disease-causing genetic variants through a combination of real-time genomic data analysis and intuitive visualization. The quickest way to get an idea of the features and functionality is to watch the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Pj5WinfmzAs&quot;&gt;intro screencast&lt;/a&gt;, quite professionally voiced over by our own Alistair Ward!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://gene.iobio.io&quot;&gt;Gene.iobio&lt;/a&gt; integrates many tools and data sources into a single intuitive and user-friendly web interface. The app allows a researcher to rapidly examine genetic variants in a patient sample according to predicted functional impact (determined via &lt;a href=&quot;http://snpeff.sourceforge.net/&quot;&gt;snpEff&lt;/a&gt;), and in the context of the pattern of inheritance from the parents. It supports the visualization of sequence alignments in the samples to assess coverage, and even to call potentially missed variants in real time. The app also pulls in data from &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.1000genomes.org/&quot;&gt;1000 Genomes Project&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://exac.broadinstitute.org/about&quot;&gt;ExAC&lt;/a&gt; to see if a given variant in the patient is common or rare in the general population. Additional touches include the ability to reanalyze variant impact from non-canonical transcripts / gene models.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Importantly, gene.iobio (just like all iobio apps) does not require any data upload. You can simply select the data files and the gene of interest, and the app fetches all the data in that gene in a couple of seconds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the &lt;a href=&quot;http://gene.iobio.io&quot;&gt;gene.iobio&lt;/a&gt; website you can find additional &lt;a href=&quot;http://gene.iobio.io/videos.html&quot;&gt;screencasts&lt;/a&gt; and descriptions of several practical &lt;a href=&quot;http://gene.iobio.io/usecases.html&quot;&gt;use cases&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are very excited about this app and hope to continue to improve it. If you have any questions or feedback leave a comment below or email us at iobioproject@gmail.com&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Install Locally Via Docker</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2015/07/05/install-locally-via-docker/"/>
   <updated>2015-07-05T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2015/07/05/install-locally-via-docker</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Often people need to run iobio apps locally. Two common reasons are to work with sensitive data that can not leave your organizations network or to have more control of deployment and access. This can be a complicated process since it requires the installation of the multiple web services that support an iobio web app. To make this easier, We have created several docker images so that the process is greatly simplified and can now be completed with just a few commands. Depending on your particular needs and infrastructure design, docker based installation can be done in several modes. In the following sessions, each of these modes are discussed in respect to particular apps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;bamiobio&quot;&gt;bam.iobio&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have a local directory, or locally mounted network directory, which contains bam files you would like to visualize inside bam.iobio, you can spin up the whole stack of bam.iobio via docker-compose. First create a directory and inside which create a docker-compose.yaml that looks something like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-yaml highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;data&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;image&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;nginx&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;volumes&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;/mnt/storage:/usr/share/nginx/html:ro&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;bamiobio&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;image&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;qiaoy/iobio-bundle.bam-iobio&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;links&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;data&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;ports&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;8000:80&quot;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;environment&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;PUB_HOSTNAME&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;bam.iobio.local&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;PUB_HTTP_PORT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;8000&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;or using a shell script without docker-compose&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-sh highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;#!/bin/bash&lt;/span&gt;
docker run &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;--name&lt;/span&gt; data &lt;span class=&quot;se&quot;&gt;\&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;-v&lt;/span&gt; /mnt/storage:/usr/share/nginx/html:ro &lt;span class=&quot;se&quot;&gt;\&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;-d&lt;/span&gt; nginx

docker run &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;--name&lt;/span&gt; bamiobio &lt;span class=&quot;se&quot;&gt;\&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;--link&lt;/span&gt; data:data &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;-p&lt;/span&gt; 8000:80 &lt;span class=&quot;se&quot;&gt;\&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;-e&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;PUB_HOSTNAME&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;bam.iobio.local &lt;span class=&quot;se&quot;&gt;\&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;-e&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;PUB_HTTP_PORT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;8000 &lt;span class=&quot;se&quot;&gt;\&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;-d&lt;/span&gt; qiaoy/iobio-bundle.bam-iobio
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If your files are already accessibly over http, or you are planning on using the local file feature only, you can omit the nginx container and the linking, i.e.:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-yaml highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;bamiobio&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;image&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;qiaoy/iobio-bundle.bam-iobio&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;ports&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;8000:80&quot;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;environment&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;PUB_HOSTNAME&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;bam.iobio.local&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;PUB_HTTP_PORT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;8000&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;or using a shell script without docker-compose&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-sh highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;#!/bin/bash&lt;/span&gt;
docker run &lt;span class=&quot;se&quot;&gt;\&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;--name&lt;/span&gt; bamiobio &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;-p&lt;/span&gt; 8000:80 &lt;span class=&quot;se&quot;&gt;\&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;-e&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;PUB_HOSTNAME&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;bam.iobio.local &lt;span class=&quot;se&quot;&gt;\&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;-e&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;PUB_HTTP_PORT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;8000 &lt;span class=&quot;se&quot;&gt;\&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;-d&lt;/span&gt; qiaoy/iobio-bundle.bam-iobio
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some explanations:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;volumes: /mnt/storage:/usr/share/nginx/html:ro&lt;/code&gt; maps the local directory &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;/mnt/storage&lt;/code&gt; into the www-root of the nginx service, so that files inside the directory can be accessed via http from within the bam.iobio bundle container&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;ports: -&quot;8000:80&quot;&lt;/code&gt; defines port mapping of 8000 on the host to 80 inside the container. The web app is always served on port 80 inside the container. You can, however, choose a different port (e.g. 80) on the host side, but make sure you also change the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;PUB_HTTP_PORT&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;PUB_HOSTNAME: bam.iobio.local&lt;/code&gt; defines a public accessible hostname to the host that is serving the web app. The content of this field, along with &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;PUB_HTTP_PORT&lt;/code&gt;, will be used to modify the javascript inside bam.iobio so that the client knows where to connect. Note that this hostname / port combination needs to be also valid from within the container, which is usually the case if you provide the Full-Qualified Domain Name of the host server. We have, however, witnessed weird network topologies that the ip address of hostname is not accessible from within the host. See below for special cases&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;PUB_HTTP_PORT: 8000&lt;/code&gt; is the port mapped on the host side. If you change the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;ports: &quot;8000:80&quot;&lt;/code&gt; line, you need to make sure that they match up with this environment variable&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the file in place, you can spin up the stack with&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-bash highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;$ &lt;/span&gt;docker-compose up
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and navigate to &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;http://${PUB_HOSTNAME}:${PUB_HTTP_PORT}/&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To visualize files in &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;/mnt/storage&lt;/code&gt;, e.g. &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;/mnt/storage/project1/patient1/diagnosis_tumor.bam&lt;/code&gt;, click on “choose bam url” from the main page, and give it &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;http://data/project1/patient1/diagnosis_tumor.bam&lt;/code&gt; (note that the file needs to be indexed first, i.e. the file &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;/mnt/storage/project1/patient1/diagnosis_tumor.bam.bai&lt;/code&gt; needs to exist).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;special-cases&quot;&gt;Special cases&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;trying-to-run-with-localhost-being-the-pub_hostname&quot;&gt;Trying to run with &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;localhost&lt;/code&gt; being the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;PUB_HOSTNAME&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The meaning of localhost differs between from within the container and from without. When it is outside of the container, localhost means the docker host machine, and the port to the reverse proxy inside the container is the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;PUB_HTTP_PORT&lt;/code&gt;; when inside the container, localhost means the virtual ethernet interface private to the container, and the port to the reverse proxy is always &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;80&lt;/code&gt;. Thus if you use &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;localhost&lt;/code&gt; as the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;PUB_HOSTNAME&lt;/code&gt;, and &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;PUB_HTTP_PORT&lt;/code&gt; some value other than &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;80&lt;/code&gt;, the client app running inside the browser will be able to make the first hop of the connection, but the iobio service will not be able to make the second because &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;${PUB_HOSTNAME}:${PUB_HTTP_PORT}&lt;/code&gt; does not correspond to a valid service address from within the container. &lt;strong&gt;WORKAROUND&lt;/strong&gt;: always use &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;PUB_HTTP_PORT=80&lt;/code&gt; if you want to use &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;localhost&lt;/code&gt; as the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;PUB_HOSTNAME&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;different-ip-address-between-from-inside-the-host-machine-and-from-outside&quot;&gt;Different IP address between from inside the host machine and from outside&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have a high performance server hosted at a server center, with a hostname &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;server.iobio&lt;/code&gt; (of course fake). From our workstations, the hostname resolves to IP address &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;x.x.x.x&lt;/code&gt;, whereas the address attached to the actual ethernet interface is &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;y.y.y.y&lt;/code&gt;. Moreover, from within the container, the hostname resolves to &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;y.y.y.y&lt;/code&gt;, which is unreachable from inside the container for some reason. So pretty much the only way to access the services within the container is to use &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;http://127.0.0.1:80/&lt;/code&gt;. &lt;strong&gt;WORKAROUND&lt;/strong&gt;: Use &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;80&lt;/code&gt; for &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;PUB_HTTP_PORT&lt;/code&gt;, and add a segment to the docker-compose.yml that looks like&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-yaml highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;bamiobio&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;...&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;extra_hosts&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;server.iobio:127.0.0.1&quot;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This ensures that when the client connects to the service, &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;http://server.iobio/&lt;/code&gt; resolves to &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;http://x.x.x.x/&lt;/code&gt;, but when a service connects to another service, &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;http://server.iobio&lt;/code&gt; resolves to &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;http://127.0.0.1&lt;/code&gt;. Because within the container the reverse proxy always listens on port 80, &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;PUB_HTTP_PORT&lt;/code&gt; has to be 80 as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;vcfiobio&quot;&gt;vcf.iobio&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The bundle image is made in a very similar way as bam.iobio, thus it is only necessary to change the image name in the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;docker-compose.yml&lt;/code&gt; file or the shell script.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-yaml highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;data&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;image&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;nginx&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;volumes&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;/mnt/storage:/usr/share/nginx/html:ro&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;bamiobio&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;image&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;qiaoy/iobio-bundle.vcf-iobio&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;links&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;data&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;ports&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;8000:80&quot;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;environment&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;PUB_HOSTNAME&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;vcf.iobio.local&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;PUB_HTTP_PORT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;8000&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The vcf files need to be bgzipped and indexed by tabix(now part of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.htslib.org&quot;&gt;htslib&lt;/a&gt;) for vcf.iobio to load. The discussion on special cases for bam.iobio also applies here.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Pacbio Alignments In Bam.iobio</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2015/04/15/pacbio-alignments-in-bam.iobio/"/>
   <updated>2015-04-15T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2015/04/15/pacbio-alignments-in-bam.iobio</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The Schatz lab just posted some &lt;a href=&quot;http://schatzlab.cshl.edu/data/skbr3/&quot;&gt;pacbio bam files&lt;/a&gt;. A quick look shows a few interesting things, such as the read length looks like it clusters below 5k, but has consistent longer reads all the way out to 30k&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/public/images/blog/pacbio_readlength.png&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://bam.iobio.io/?bam=http://labshare.cshl.edu/shares/schatzlab/www-data/skbr3/SKBR3_Feb17_GRCh38.sorted.bam&amp;amp;region=chr1&quot;&gt;Check out the rest in bam.iobio&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Vcf.iobio Released</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2014/11/25/vcf-iobio-released/"/>
   <updated>2014-11-25T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2014/11/25/vcf-iobio-released</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;We are releasing our second iobio app today, &lt;a href=&quot;http://vcf.iobio.io/&quot;&gt;vcf.iobio&lt;/a&gt;. Vcf.iobio is a data QC app simliar to bam.iobio, but for variant data in the vcf format. Metrics such as allele frequency spectrum, TSTV ratio, variant quality distribution and more are calcuated for both remote and local files.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Univeristy of Utah Blog Post on Bam.iobio</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2014/11/25/utah-health-care-post/"/>
   <updated>2014-11-25T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2014/11/25/utah-health-care-post</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;University of Utah’s Health Care Blog did a quick &lt;a href=&quot;http://healthcare.utah.edu/publicaffairs/news/2014/11/11-25-14-Bam.iobio-Interactive-Sequence-Alignment-App.php&quot;&gt;writeup&lt;/a&gt; on the bam.iobio publication in the Nature Methods.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Scope Radio Interview</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2014/11/25/scope-radio-interview/"/>
   <updated>2014-11-25T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2014/11/25/scope-radio-interview</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Here’s an interview I did with Scope Radio on bam.iobio and iobio in general. &lt;a href=&quot;http://healthcare.utah.edu/the-scope/shows.php?shows=0_djpfw8ee&quot;&gt;Listen here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Bam.iobio published</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2014/11/25/bam-iobio-published/"/>
   <updated>2014-11-25T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2014/11/25/bam-iobio-published</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;We are very excited to announce that the first iobio app, bam.iobio, has been &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nature.com/nmeth/journal/v11/n12/full/nmeth.3174.html&quot;&gt;published in nature methods&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 

</feed>
